<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A very necessarie and profitable booke concerning nauigation, compiled in Latin by Ioannes Taisnierus, a publice professor in Rome, Ferraria, &amp; other uniuersities in Italie of the mathematicalles, named a treatise of continuall motions. Translated into Englishe, by Richard Eden. The contents of this booke you shall finde on the next page folowyng</title>
            <author>Taisnier, Jean, 1508-ca. 1562.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23659</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101247</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837063</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837063</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1369</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13348)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1369)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 977:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A very necessarie and profitable booke concerning nauigation, compiled in Latin by Ioannes Taisnierus, a publice professor in Rome, Ferraria, &amp; other uniuersities in Italie of the mathematicalles, named a treatise of continuall motions. Translated into Englishe, by Richard Eden. The contents of this booke you shall finde on the next page folowyng</title>
                  <author>Taisnier, Jean, 1508-ca. 1562.</author>
                  <author>Eden, Richard, 1521?-1576.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[84] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Iugge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1575?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [three aserisks] A-D E² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Michigan. William Clements Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Navigation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ A very neceſſarie and <hi>profitable Booke concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> Nauigation, compiled in</hi> Latin by <hi>Ioannes Taiſnie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> a publike profeſſor in Rome, <hi>Ferraria,</hi> &amp; other Vniuerſities in <hi>Italie</hi> of the Mathematicalles, named a treatiſe of continuall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated into Engliſhe, by <hi>Richarde Eden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The contentes of this booke you ſhall finde on the next page folowyng.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Imprinted at London by Richarde Iugge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>publisher's device (?)</figDesc>
               <q>OMNIA DESVPER</q>
               <signed>R. I.</signed>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F the marueylous nature and vertue of the Lode ſtone, called in Latin <hi>Magnes,</hi> where they be found, and howe to knowe the beſt.</item>
               <item>2 Of continual motion by the ſayd ſtone, <hi>Magnes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 Of the due proportion of whatſoeuer Ship, and the diſcloſyng of certayne Mathematicall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes.</item>
               <item>4 Of ebbyng and flowyng, with their diuerſities, and the cauſes thereof.</item>
               <item>5 Demonſtrations of proportion of motions local, confutyng the opinion of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> therein.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the ryght woorshipfull Syr <hi>Wylliam Wynter, Knyght, Maister</hi> of the Ordinaunce of the Queenes Maieſties <hi>Shippes, and Surueyor of the ſayd Shippes. <hi>Richarde Eden wyſheth health and prosperitie.</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is nowe about twelue yeeres paſte (gentle Maiſter Wynter) ſince the curteſie and fauour which long before I founde at your hande, mooued me no leſſe for the good wyll that I haue euer borne you and your vertues, to excogitate or deuiſe ſomethyng, within the compaſſe of my poore abilitie, that myght be a witneſſe, &amp; as it were a ſeale, to teſtifie both that I haue not forgotten your gentleneſſe, &amp; alſo howe deſyrous I am to pay the debtes of freendſhyp which then I promiſed you, &amp; alſo attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to perfourme: But beyng at that tyme preuented, by meanes of my ſodayne departyng out of Englande, with my good Lorde the <hi>Vidame,</hi> with whom I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned for the ſpace of ten yeeres, vntyll the calamities of that miſerable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, with loſſe of goods, and danger of lyfe, hath dryuen me home agayne into my natiue countrey: Where fyndyng my ſelfe at ſome leyſure, and deſyrous to paſſe foorth parte of my tyme in ſome honeſt exerciſe, which myght be profytable to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, domagable to none, and a meanes to geat me newe freendes, the olde in my ſo long abſence, in maner vtterly waſted: I chaunced in the meane tyme, to meete with my olde acquayntance and freend, Richard Iugge, Printer to the Queenes Maieſtie, who had many yeeres before, printed the Booke of <hi>Matten Curtes,</hi> of the Art of Nauigation, by me tranſlated out of the Spanyſhe tongue. Whereof, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng with him ſome conference, he declared that he woulde prynt that booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, yf I woulde take the paynes to deuiſe ſome addition touchyng the ſame matter, that myght be ioyned thereto. At whiche tyme, hauyng with me in the Latine tongue, theſe bookes here folowyng printed, whiche I brought with me out of Fraunce, I ſoone agreed to his honeſt requeſt, to tranſlate them into Englyſhe: Whiche beyng accomplyſhed, this onely remayned, accordyng to the common cuſtome, to conſecrate and dedicate the ſame to ſome worthie perſonage, whoſe fame, auchoritie, and dignitie, myght defende them from the euyll tongues of ſuch as are more redie rather to reprooue other mens dooynges, then to doo any good them ſelues. And therfore (gentle Maiſter Wynter) knowing your auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and fame in well deſeruyng, and honorable ſeruice vnto your Prince and Countrey, to be ſuche as all men thynke ſo well of, and ſo greatlye eſteeme, to whom (rather then vnto you) may I dedicate this booke of Nauigation? In conſyderation whereof, and the hope that I haue in your approoued curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, fauourably to accept this dedication, as proceeyng from one that deſyreth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng more then to doo you ſeruice, and remayne in your grace, I ſhall thynke my trauayle wel beſtowed, and ſufficiently recompenced, yf it ſhall pleaſe you to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the ſame as thankfully, as I wyllyngly offer it vnto you. For yf there be any thyng in me, wherein I maye by good reaſon pleaſe my ſelfe, it is cheefely this,
<pb facs="tcp:1369:3"/> that I haue euer loued and honoured men of ſinguler vertue or qualitie, in what ſo euer laudable Art or Science, euen of thoſe whereof I mee ſelfe haue litle knowledge, as are Geometrie, Aſtronomie, Architecture, Muſicke, Payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, feates of Armes, inuentions of Ingens, and ſuche lyke: Of the whiche, this our age maye ſeeme not onely to contende with the Auncientes, but alſo in many goodly inuentions of Art and wyt, farre to exceede them. For (not to ſpeake agaynſt all the marueylous inuentions of our tyme) what of theirs is to be compared to the Artes of Printyng, makyng of Gunnes, Fyre woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, of ſundry kyndes of artificial Fyres, of ſuche marueylous force, that moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes of moſte harde rockes and ſtones, are not able to reſyſt their violence, but art by them broken in peeces, and throwen into the ayre with ſuche violence, that neyther the ſpirite of <hi>Demogorgon,</hi> or the thunderboltes of infernal <hi>Pluto</hi> can doo the lyke. What ſhoulde I here ſpeake of the woonderfull inuentions of <hi>Fartalio,</hi> in his booke <hi>De Arte maiori?</hi> or of many other, wherof <hi>Vannucius Beringocius</hi> wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in his booke, entituled <hi>Pytotechnia.</hi> As touchyng which terrible inuentions, and the lyke, although ſome men be of opinion that they were inuented by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of the deuyll, for the deſtruction of mankynde: yet other weyghyng the matter more indifferently, thynke that the inuention of Gunnes hath been the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of many mens lyues, becauſe before the vſe of them, men were not woont ſo long tyme to lye batteryng in the beſiegyng of Townes or Fortreſſes, but in ſhort ſpace to come to hande ſtrokes, and to ſoughten feeldes, to the great ſlaughter of great multitudes. And ſeeyng that nowe our enimies the Turkes, and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, haue the vſe of theſe deuylyſhe inuentions (as they name them) it may be thought requiſite for vs, agaynſt ſuche deuylles to vſe alſo the lyke deuylyſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, leſt refuſyng the ſame, and geuyng place to euyl, we ſhoulde wyllyngly ſuffer the kyngdome of the deuyll to triumphe ouer vs, not otherwyſe able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſt, and much leſſe to ouercome ſo puiſſant and horrible enimies (except beſyde al hope) myght aryſe in our defence ſome newe Moyſes, or Elias, or the Prieſtes of Iericho, whiche onely with the noyſe and ſounde of Hornes or Trumpettes ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threwe the walles of the towne. Neyther wyl the example of Dauid and Goliath, or of Samſon and the Philiſtines, ſerue our turne at this tyme, although I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that the arme of the Lorde is not weakened, yf there lacked not a Moyſes with his rodde, and woorthie Aſſyſtentes, which myght helpe to holde vp his wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye arme. But to returne to ſpeake of ingens, and ingenious inuentions, whiche inuented and vſed to the glorie of God, and defence of his people, againſt the furie and tyrannie of Infidelles, they may as woorthyly be called the gyftes of God, as were the inuentions and Art of them that buylded eyther the Temple of Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, or the Arke of God: And yet is it there wrytten of thoſe Artificers, that God gaue them the ſpirite of knowledge and cunnyng in ſuche Artes. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thynke it may alſo be ſayde without offence,<note place="margin">Exod. xxxv. Bezaleel and Ahaliab.</note> that the knowledge of <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes,</hi> and other men in ſuche commendable inuentions, are the gyftes of God, for as muche as the gyftes of God are free, and not bounde to any nation or perſon. And yf it may be graunted that the ſpirites of men, or the ſpirite of God in men, may be diuided (as was the ſpirite of Moyſes to twelue other) or otherwyſe that the ſpirites of dead men may reuiue in other (after the opinion and tranſanimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Pythagoras</hi>) we may thynke that the ſoule of <hi>Archimedes</hi> was reuiued in <hi>Beſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> that excellent Geometer of our tyme, whom I knewe in Fraunce the Maiſter of the engins to the Frenche kyng, Charles the nienth, vnder whom that lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſlaughter at <hi>Paris</hi> was committed, in the whiche were ſlayne ſo many noble men. Whiche crueltie the ſayde <hi>Beſson</hi> abhorryng, fled hyther into England, and
<pb facs="tcp:1369:3"/> here dyed, in the yeere. 1573. and left in witneſſe of his excellencie in that Art, a booke in prynt, conteynyng the fourmes and portractes of ſyxtie engins of marueylous ſtrange and profytable deuice, for diuers commodious and neceſſary vſes. Of the whiche, for as muche as three of them, that is to meane, the .54. 57. and 60. be engines cheefely parteynyng vnto Shyppes, it ſhall not be from my purpoſe here to make a breefe rehearſal of them. The .54. therefore (as he wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) is an engin not vnlyke vnto that whiche in auncient tyme <hi>Archimedes</hi> inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the <hi>Syracuſians,</hi> wherewith a man with the ſtrength of onely one hande, by helpe of the inſtrument called <hi>Triſpaſton</hi> (which in our tongue ſome cal an endleſſe Serue, brought a Shyp of marueylous greatneſſe from the lande into the ſea, in the ſyght of kyng <hi>Hieron,</hi> and an infinite multitude, whiche with all their force coulde not doo the ſame. &amp;c. Of the which alſo, our countrey man, Roger Bacon,<note place="margin">Of this inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, reade the Coſmola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be of Beſson.</note> a great Philoſopher (and no Nicromancer, as that ignorant age ſlaundered him) ſeemed to haue had ſome knowledge: For in his booke of the marueylous power of Art and Nature, he maketh mention of an Inſtrument (as farre as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) no bygger than a mans hande, wherewith one man myght drawe to hym the ſtrength of three hundred men. And I well remember, that at my beyng in Fraunce, I hearde credible reporte, that the Earle of <hi>Rocum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>fe,</hi> an Almaine, made an engin, wherewith the ſayde kyng Charles when he was but .xvi. yeeres of age, lyfted from the grounde a weyght, whiche the ſtrongeſt man in the courte was not able to remooue. Almoſte the lyke deuice we ſee in the bendyng of a Croſſebowe. Alſo at my being in Germanie in the citie of Stroſburge, a woorthy and learned Gentleman, <hi>Monſieur de Saleno,</hi> tolde me that in that citie one had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented an engin of iron, no bygger then a mans hande, wherevnto faſtenyng a rope, with a hooke of iron, and caſtyng the hooke vpon a wal, tree, or other place, where it myght take holde, he coulde with that engin lyft hym ſelfe vp to the wal, or other place. But to returne to the other two engines of <hi>Beſson,</hi> parteynyng to our purpoſe. Therefore the .60. fygure (as he there wryteth) is the inuention of an engin, ſcarſely credible, wherewith by ballance and eaſie motion, beyond the order of nature, a Shyp may be ſo framed and gouerned, that in the calme ſea it ſhall mooue forewarde, and in litle wynde haſten the courſe, &amp; in too much wynde temper and moderate the ſame: A thyng woorth the knowledge to a kyng, as he ſayth. Of the thyrd engin, which is the .57. fygure of his booke, he wryteth thus, An Artifice not yet diuulgate or ſet forth, whiche placed in the pompe of a Shyp, whyther the water hath recourſe, and mooued by the motion of the Shyp, with wheeles and weyghtes, dooth exactly ſhewe what ſpace the Shyp hath gone. &amp;c. By whiche deſcription, ſome doo vnderſtand that the knowledge of the longitude myght ſo be founde, a thyng doubtleſſe greatly to be deſyred, and hytherto not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynely knowen, although <hi>Sebaſtian Cabot</hi> on his death bed tolde me that he has the knowledge thereof by diuine reuelation, yet ſo, that he myght not teache any man. But I thinke that the good olde man, in that extreme age, ſomewhat doted, and had not yet euen in the article of death, vtterly ſhaken of all worldlye vayne glorie. As touchyng whiche knowledge of the longitude, to ſpeake a litle more b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> occaſion nowe geuen, it ſhal not be from the purpoſe, to rehearſe the ſaying of that excellent learned man, <hi>Iohannes Feruclius,</hi> in his incomparable booke <hi>De ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cauſis,</hi> where in the Preface to king Henrie of Fraunce, he writeth in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. We haue put our helpyng hande to the Art of Nauigation and Geographie: forby obſeruation of the houres of the Equinoctialles, we haue inuented howe, in what ſo euer region or place of the worlde a man ſhalbe, he may knowe in what longitude it is: which certaynly we haue not taken of the fountaynes of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes, but fyrſte, of all other (as I thynke) haue drawen it of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ryuers, as our
<pb facs="tcp:1369:4"/> owne inuention. &amp;c. So that (ſaith be) whiche way ſo euer you turne your eyes, you may ſee that the poſteritie hath not ryotouſly waſted the inheritance of Artes and ſciences, left them by their predeceſſors, but haue greatly encreaſed the ſame, and inuented other: For certaynely, the multitude of thinges incomprehenſible, is infinite, and ſo therfore inuentions muſt needes alſo be infinite, &amp; without ende. And therefore, as touchyng this thing (ſayth he) to ſpeake freely what I thynke, they ſeeme to me to offende as muche, whiche contende that the auncientes haue inuented and comprehended al thynges, as doo they whiche attribute not vnto them the fyrſt inuentions, ſo depryuyng them of theyr ryght poſſeſſion. For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as nowe by the benefite of almyghtie God (who hath geuen vs his Chriſte, and with hym all good thynges) the lyght of trueth ſhyneth in our vnderſtandyng by godly inſpiration, there is no iuſt cauſe why we ſhoulde in ſuche thynges thinke vs inferior to the auncientes. Of which Argument, who lyſteth may reade more in the ſayde Epiſtle of <hi>Pernelius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">An inſtrument in motion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeyng with the motion of heauen. Anno Dom. 1584.</note> And for as much as I haue made mention of ſuch inuentions, it ſhal not be from the purpoſe, to deſcribe the goodly inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Angelus Policianus</hi> in the fourth booke of Epiſtles to <hi>Franciſcus Caſa,</hi> wryteth in this maner, I haue receyued your Epiſtle, wherein you ſignifie vnto me, that you haue hearde of the ſtrange engine or inſtrument <hi>Antomaton</hi> inuented, and made of late by one Laurence a Florentine: in the which is expreſſed the courſe and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Planettes, comformable and agreeyng with the motions of heauen: And that (for as muche as the reporte thereof is hardly beleeued) you greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre that I ſhould write vnto you, what certayne knowledge I haue of that thing, wherein I am redie to obey your requeſt. And although nowe it be long ſince I ſawe it, yet as farre as I beare in memorie, I wyll breefely declare the fourme, reaſon, and vſe thereof. And yf the deſcription of it ſhal ſeeme vnto you ſomewha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obſcure, you ſhall not aſcribe it altogether to my declaration, but partly to the ſubtiltie &amp; nouiltie of the thyng. It is in fourme of a ſquare pyller, ſharpe toward the top, in maner of a <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> of the height of almoſt three cubites: ouer or aboue it, in maner of a couer, is a flat or playne rounde plate of gylted copper, garnyſhed with ſundry colours, on whoſe other part is expreſſed the whole courſe of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and whoſe dimention or meaſure is ſomewhat ſhorter then a cubite, and is within turned or mooued with certayne litle denticle wheeles, an immouable cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle comprehendyng the hygheſt border or margent, and diuided with the ſpaces of xxiiii. houres within it, in the hygheſt turnyng rundel, the twelue ſignes are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by three degrees. Further, within are ſeene eyght runde is, in maner all of one greatneſſe. Of theſe, two obteyne the myddle poynt, the one faſtened in the other, ſo that the loweſt beyng ſomewhat bygger, repreſenteth the Sunne, and the hygher the Moone. From the Sunne a beame commyng to the circle, ſheweth in it the houres: and in the Zodiacke, the monethes, dayes, and number of degrees, and alſo the true and halfe motion of the Sunne. From the Moone alſo procedeth a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne, or wyre, whiche beneathe or downwarde in the border or margent of the greateſt rundell, ſheweth the houres: and paſſyng by the center of the Epicicle of the Moone, and extendyng to the Zodiacke, ſheweth the halfe motion of his Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. Another alſo ryſyng from thence, and cuttyng the border of the center of the Moone (that is of the Epicicle) ſheweth her true place, whereby art ſeene the ſlowneſſe, ſwyftneſſe, al motions and courſes, coniunctions alſo, and ful Moones. About theſe are ſyxe other rundels: of the whiche, one, whom they call the head and tayle of the Dragon, ſheweth the Eclipſes both of the Sunne and Moone. The other are attributed to the Planets: from euery of whiche, proceede two pay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es, aſſigning the motions (as we haue ſayd) of the Moone: but they alſo goe backwarde, whiche chaunceth not in the Moone, whoſe Eclipſe is mooued con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywyſe.
<pb facs="tcp:1369:4"/> And thus the reaſon of coniunctions, departynges, and latitudes, is manifeſt in all. There is alſo an other border lyke vnto a Zodiacke, cutting or diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng vpwarde or aboue, thoſe ſyx litle rundels (whereof we haue ſpoken) being the rundels of the Planettes: whereby appeareth the degrees of the Eaſt ſignes, and the ſpaces of the dayes (that is to ſay) at what houre the Sunne riſeth, by the whiche, euery of the Planettes are carried in their rundels or circles by courſe, in the day tyme to the Eaſt, and in the nyght to the Weſt. Agayne contrarywyſe, the greateſt rundel of al, draweth with it al the Planettes, in the nyght to the Eaſt, and in the day to the Weſt, in the ſpace of .24. houres. At which, to agree with the motions of heauen, both reaſon and experience doo confyrme: And therfore ought ye not to marueyle, yf theſe thynges ſeeme incredible to many. For (as ſayth the wyſe Prouerve) fayth is ſlowlye geuen to great thynges, for euen we ſcarſely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue our owne eyes, when we ſee ſuche thynges. And therefore, whereas in tyme paſt I read, that ſuche a lyke inſtrument was made by <hi>Archimedes,</hi> my fayth yet fayled me to geue credite to ſo great an Aucthour, which thyng neuertheleſſe this our Florentine hath perfourmed. The worke doubtleſſe beyng of ſuch excellence, that all prayſe is inferior to it, and can not therfore for the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>thyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe thereof be otherwyſe prayſed, then to ſay that it paſſeth all prayſe. The Artificer him ſelfe alſo being a man of ſuch integritie of maners, that the ſunne is nothing inferior to the excellencie of his wyt: in ſo much that he may ſeeme a man ſent from heauen, where be learned the makyng of this heauen, by the example of the other. Hyther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Policianus.</hi> Of the lyke inſtrument, Roger Bacon alſo maketh mention in his ſayde booke, of the marueylous power of Art and nature, affyrmynge the ſame to be woorth a kyngdome to a wyſe man. But for as muche as the ſubiect whiche I haue nowe in hande, is cheefely touchyng inuentions parteinyng to Shyppes, and the Art of Nauigation, I thynke good to ſpeake ſomewhat of the inuention of a certayne Italian wryter, named <hi>Leonardo F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ananti,</hi> who in his booke, entituled,<note place="margin">Lib. 3. Ca. 18</note> 
               <hi>Specchio diſcientia vniuerſale,</hi> doeth greatly glory in the inuention of Shyppes, whiche can not peryſhe eyther on the ſea, or the lande,<note place="margin">The inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Shyp which can not be drowned.</note> affyrmyng that the lyke was neuer inuented ſince the creation of the worlde. But I feare me, leſt vayne glorie of diſcourſyng in the Italian tongue, hath cauſed him more then needes, to commende his owne inuention, as for the moſte parte is the maner of the Italian writers. Therfore committing the iudgement hereof to men of greater experience and knowledge in theſe thynges, I wyl onely tranſlate his woordes, whereby in the booke before named, he deſcribeth the ſayde Shyppe in this maner. Take beames of Fyrre, or Pyne tree, which of their owne nature can neuer goe downe, or ſyncke, or abyde vnder the water, and with theſe beames frame an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ne (<hi>Machina,</hi> yf I may ſo call it) of the length of three ſcore foure, and of the breadth of twentie foote, and of the heyght of ſyxe foote, laying the fyrſte ranke in length, and the other trauerſe, or ouerthwarte, and the thyrde agayne in length, faſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyng the ſore parte lyke vnto other Shyppes, and in lyke maner, bryngyng the poupe or hynder parte to good fourme: then with ſuche irons as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pparteyne, bynde it, and ſtrengthen it in ſuche maner that it can not breake. And vpon this frame or fundation buylde your Shyppe, of ſuche faſhion as you thynke beſt. &amp;c. It were here too long to rehearſe with what proude woordes and oſtentation he magnifieth this inuention. But whether this frame or engine ſhoulde be bylden vpon the keele or bottome of the Shyp, or otherwyſe, I commit it to them of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iudgement, as I haue ſayde. But wheras it may for this tyme ſuffice to haue wrytten thus muche of theſe thynges, I wyll make an ende with onely a br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te rehearſal of the inuention and encreaſe of the Art of Nauigation.</p>
            <p>After that the Art of Nauigation was founde, euery man began to chalenge vnto
<pb facs="tcp:1369:5"/> hym the dominion of the ſea, &amp; there to dwel and kepe warre euen as on the land.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Minos</hi> (as wryteth <hi>Strabo</hi>) was the fyrſt that ruled on the ſea, whiche neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, other aſcribe to <hi>Neptunus,</hi> who fyrſt founde the Art of Nauigation, and was therefore (as wryteth <hi>Diodorus</hi>) appoynted by <hi>Saturnus</hi> to be Admiral of the fyrſte Nauie: and thereby the poſteritie afterwarde aſcribed to him the gouernaunce of the ſea, and named him the God thereof. After whom the <hi>Cretenſes</hi> euer were eſteemed moſt expert in the Art of Nauigation. But (as wryteth Pliuie) boates were fyrſt inuented, and with them was the fyrſte ſaylyng in the Ilandes of the redde ſea, vnder kyng <hi>Erythra,</hi> as alſo witneſſeth <hi>Quintilian,</hi> ſaying, If none had proceeded further then the inuentions of our predeceſſors, we had had nothyng in the Poets aboue <hi>Andronicus,</hi> and nothyng in hiſtories aboue the <hi>Annales</hi> or Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles of Byſhoppes, and had yet haue ſayled in troughes or in boates. Other haue aſcribed this inuention to diuers other nations and perſons, as to the Troians and Myſians in <hi>Helleſponto,</hi> and alſo that the ancient Britanes made boates of leather or hydes, and ſayled with them in the Ocean ſea. Plinie wryteth, that <hi>Danaus</hi> was the fyrſt that brought a Shyppe out of Grece into Egypt. Some alſo geue the ſame to <hi>Minerua.</hi> But moſt ryghtfully, the inuention both of the Shyp, and Art of Nauigation, is aſcribed to Noe, who (as wryteth <hi>Euſebius</hi>) was long before <hi>Neptune</hi> or <hi>Danaus.</hi> For doubteleſſe (ſayth he) the Arke of Noe was none other then a Shyp, and the fyrſte and onely exemplar of the buyldyng of all other Shyppes or veſſelles of ſaylyng. Alſo the moſte ancient wryter <hi>Beroſus</hi> the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dean (as wryteth <hi>Ioſephus</hi>) calleth the Arke of Noe, a Shyp. The ſame <hi>Ioſephus</hi> alſo ſayth, that the Nephues of Noe, departyng to inhabite diuers partes of the worlde, vſed many Shyppes. &amp;c. Long after Noe, the <hi>Tyrians</hi> were counted moſt expert in the Art of Nauigation: and after them, diuers other nations. For wheras no Art is ſo perfect, but may receyue encreaſe, hereof doth it folowe, that this Art alſo hath been greatly augmented, and brought to further perfection by witty inuentions of the poſteritie, euen vnto our age: wherof, who ſo lyſteth to knowe further more particulerly who inuented all other partes and inſtrumentes partey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to al ſortes of Shyppes, &amp; Art of Nauigation, may reade y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde booke of Polidor Virgil, <hi>Cap. xv, De Inuentorib. Rer.</hi> and <hi>Bayfius, de re nauali.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus gentle Maiſter Wynter, beſeechyng your woorſhyp to take in good part this teſtimonie of my thankfull hart (ſuche as it is) I beſeeche the immortall God to proſper all your dooinges to his honor, and the benefite of your Countrey.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:5"/>
            <head>¶ To the right Reuerende father in <hi>Chriſte, and honorable Prince, Lorde</hi> Iohn Gebhard, of the Earles of Mansfelt. &amp;c. Archbiſhop of Colen, Prince elector, duke of Angaria and VVeſtphalia, hygh Chaunceler of the Romayne Empire. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE thing which to this day in maner from the beginning of the world, great Philoſophers with perpetual ſtudie and great labour, haue endeuoured to bring to effect, and deſired ende (moſt gratious Prince) hath neuertheleſſe hitherto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned eyther vnknowen, or hydde, not without great damage and hynderance of moſte expert Mathematicians and Architecteurs, and al other men of lyke practicall faculties: And yf any there haue been whiche haue attayned to the experience of this continuall motion, I ſuppoſe the ſame to haue been vexed and noted,<note place="margin">A perpetual or continuall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> with the va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne glorye of the incomparable paynter and grauer, <hi>Michael Angelo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Michael Angelo.</note> who euen at the extreme rendryng of the ſpirit of lyfe, dyd not vouchſafe to diſcloſe vnto his owne ſonne the ſecrets of his arte, eſteeming it greatly to the reputation of his fame and glory, by this ingrate hydyng of his ſcience, falſely to obteyne a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual memorie with ſuche as ſhoulde ſucceede hym: Or els truely he doubted (as is commonly ſeene in all maner of doctrine and ſcience) that there ſhoulde ſtill ryſe vp certayne malitious and enuious quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relers, and troublous wits, instigate by an euyl ſpirite, to deface and ſuppreſſe trueth with ſlaunderous tongues, especially agaynſt artes Mathematikes (of whiche kinde, are Grauyng, Payntyng, and ſuche lyke) whiche in al ages haue euer been ſubiect to this inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of ignorant detractours, except they be defended by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and title of fauourable princes. And whereas ſuche ſciences
<pb facs="tcp:1369:6"/> vnto the ignorant ſeeme ridiculus and ſuſpicious, neuertheleſſe in the frame and experience of this continuall motion, ought no ſuſpicion to be bad. And foraſmuche as the ſame is very neceſſarie and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the common wealth, I was the bolder through confidence in your hyghnes clemencie vnder the grace and title of the ſame, to put foorth this litle booke of continuall motion. The whiche howe great profite and exerciſe it may bryng to excellent men of what ſo euer facultie, experience it ſelfe ſhal eaſily declare. Moſt humbly deſiring your highneſſe, gratiouſly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this ray trauaile with ſuch as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate to the Muſes, and employ theyr labours to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of mankinde.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your hyghneſſe moſte humble ſeruant and Oratour,</hi> Iohn Taiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier Hannonius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:6"/>
            <head>¶ Of the nature and effectes of the <hi>Lode ſtone, called in Latine</hi> Magues.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a common prouerbe that in ſtones, woodes, and hearbes, conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth great vertue: which ſaying is doubtleſſe moſt manifeſt by the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience of this ſtone, beyng founde in ſundry places of India, it is ſayde alſo that it was founde in Spayne by one named <hi>Heracleon</hi> (as witneſſeth <hi>Nicander</hi>) whyle in keepyng of cattell,<note place="margin">Fiue kindes of Lode ſtones.</note> the iron nayles of his ſhowes and pyke of his ſtaffe, cleft faſt to the ſtone. Of the which <hi>Magnes,</hi> are fiue kinds as <hi>Sotacus</hi> wryteth. That is to wyt: one of Ethiopia. An other of Macedonia. The thyrde is founde in Echio of Beotia. The fourth about Troades of Alexandria.<note place="margin">Lode stone male and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male.</note> The fyfth of <hi>Magneſia Aſiae.</hi> The difference of the ſtone is, whether it be male or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male. The next difference, is in coloure: for that which is founde in Macedonia and <hi>Magneſia,</hi> is ruddiſhe and blacke. That of Beotia, is more ruddiſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blacke. That of Troades is blacke, and of female kinde, and therefore without vertue.<note place="margin">
                  <p>The beſt Lode<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtone of Hewe colour.</p>
                  <p>Lode ſtone ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d for the weight of ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uer.</p>
               </note> The worſt of <hi>Magneſia Aſiae,</hi> is whyte, and draweth not iron, and is lyke vnto a punice ſtone. They are proued the beſt which are moſt of blewe or heauenly colour. That of Ethiope is moſt prayſed, and (as <hi>Plinie</hi> ſayth) is ſolde for the weight of ſiluer. This is found in <hi>Zimri,</hi> a ſandie region of Ethiope, where is alſo founde <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matites Magnes,</hi> of blooddy colour, appearyng lyke blood yf it be grounde, and alſo lyke ſaffron, whiche in drawyng of iron,<note place="margin">One lodeſtone draweth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> is not of like vertue to the <hi>Hematites Magnes</hi> of Ethiopia, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che draweth vnto it another <hi>Magnes.</hi> All theſe be profitable for medicines of the eyes, eche of them accordyng to their portion, and do ſpecially ſtay <hi>Epiphoras</hi> (that is) droppyng of the eyes.<note place="margin">Lode stones m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And alſo beyng brunt or made in powder, they heale burninges. And not farre from the ſame place of Ethiopia, is a mountayne
<pb facs="tcp:1369:7"/> whiche bryngeth forth the ſtone called <hi>Theamedes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The stone Theamedes putteth iron from it.</note> which put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth from it, and refuſeth iron. I haue often prooued the vertue and power of the ſtone <hi>Magnes,</hi> by the needle whiche is in ſome Dialles, by the attraction thereof, moouyng it ſelfe from ſyde to ſyde, and rounde about. Although the ſtone were vnder a table, yet doeth the needle, being aboue the table, naturally folow the moouyng of the ſtone. It is therfore no marueyle yf there be great vertue in ſtones,<note place="margin">Iron nayles drawen out of Shippes by the stone.</note> woodes, and herbes. It hath alſo been prooued, that Shyppes compact with iron nayles, ſaylyng by the ſea of Ethiope, and by tempeſt dryuen to lande, to certayne capes or landes endes, haue by theſe ſtones been eyther drawen to the bottome of the ſea, or els the nayles beyng drawen out by the vertue of the ſtone, the Shyp hath fallen in a thouſande peeces. And therefore the diſcreete and ware Cantabrians, moſt expert Mariners, ſaylyng by the ſea of Ethiope, frame their Shyppes with pynnes and hoopes of wood, to auoyde the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that myght chaunce of lyke occaſion.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Agayne, of the naure, knowledge, vertue, equalitie, qualitie, and effectes of the ſtone Magnes, or the Lode ſtone.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR as muche as euery thing that is good, is ſo muche the better as it is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: therefore doo I intende to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate vnto our poſteritie, this litle woorke of the nature, effects and miracles of the ſtone <hi>Magnes.</hi> The whiche, although they may ſeeme to the ignoraunt common people, to exceede the limittes of nature, yet to expert men, and Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titians, they ſeeme not ſo ſtrange, notwithſtandyng that it is almoſt impoſſible to manyfeſt al the ſecrets and miracles thereof:<note place="margin">Art in manye thyngs paſſeth and amendeth nature.</note> For whereas Art inuenteth, and bryngeth to perfection many thynges whiche are impoſſible to nature, it is neceſſary that he who deſyreth to doo great effectes in theſe thinges, and the lyke, be very expert in woorkyng with the hande: neyther is it ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for him to be a perfect Naturaliſt, Mathematitian, or Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomer, for as muche as furthermore is requyred great dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritie of handie woorke: And for defaulte hereof, it commeth to paſſe, that in this our age theſe natural artes lie hid &amp; vnknowen.
<pb facs="tcp:1369:7"/> This ſtone is knowen by colour, vertue, weyght, and equalitie.<note place="margin">The ſtone Magnes is knowen by colour, vertue, weyght, and equalitie. Colour. Vertue. Equalitie.</note> The beſt colour, is lyke pure iron, ſhynyng, mixt with Indian or heauenly colour, &amp; is in maner like iron pooliſhed. This ſtone is alſo oftentymes found in certayne regions of the North, &amp; is brought from thence into certayne partes of Normandie and Flaunders. The experience of the vertue of this ſtone, is eaſie. For if it drawe vnto it a great weyght of iron, it is iudged to be ſtronge: &amp; the heauier alſo the better. By equalitie, it is iudged yf it be al alyke of one ſubſtance and colour: but yf it be vnequall with chappes, &amp; holow places indented, hauyng red ſpottes here and there, it is vnapt to the art of nauigation or of continual mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It repreſenteth the ſimititude of heauen. For lyke as in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are two poynts immoueable, ending the axiltre of the ſphere, vpon the which the whole frame of heauen is turned (as may be founde by the arte wherby Criſtall &amp; other ſtones are pooliſhed:) euen ſo the ſtone <hi>Magnes,</hi> reduced into a globous or rounde forme, laying thereon a needle or any other lyke iron,<note place="margin">Howe to finde the poles by the ſtone.</note> then which way ſo euer the needle turneth and reſteth, thereby is ſhewed the place of the poles. And that this may be done more certaynely, it muſt be oftentymes attempted, and the lyne ſhewed by the needle, muſt be obſerued: for ſuch lynes ſhal cut the one the other in two pointes, as the Meridian circles ioyne togeather in the poles of the worlde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſame is geathered an other way.</head>
               <p>This is done more certaynely, yf in the round ſtone (as is ſayd)
<figure>
                     <figDesc>lodestone</figDesc>
                  </figure> be found the place which oftentimes draweth iron, whiche beyng founde, yf then the poynt do exactly appeare, part of the broken needle, muſte be layde vpon the ſtone, and be ſo often by litle and litle tranſpoſed, vntyll the ſtyle or pyn by perpendicle or plom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met do directly fal vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone. For there on the contrary parte, by lyke maner ſhalbe found the other pole. A. ſhalbe the true point, and B. the falſe,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:1369:8"/>
               <head>The maner to knowe the one pole from the other.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hiche of the two poyntes aforeſayde may aunſweare to the pole Artike or the North pole, is founde in this maner. Cauſe a large veſſell to be fylled with water, in the which cauſe the ſtone <hi>Magnes</hi> to be layde vppon a lyght boorde, not deepe, muche lyke the coueryng of a boxe, ſo neuertheleſſe that the two poyntes founde in the ſtone may lye equally eleuate in
<figure>
                     <figDesc>floating lodestone</figDesc>
                  </figure> the ſayd boxe: and ſo by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone, the boxe ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be mooued to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where the meridio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall pole ſhall exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de toward the South, &amp; the other op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the North, &amp; ſhal reſt ther. And thus ſhal it be eaſye to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, whiche of the poynts anſwereth to the pole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, &amp; to the pole Antar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, ſo that the places of heauen be fyrſte knowen by anye meanes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:1369:8"/>
               <head>That one ſtone draweth another.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow one ſtone draweth another, we wil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare hereafter. Lay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one (as is ſayd) vpon a boorde or boxe in the water, that it may freely flote, &amp; hold an other in your hande. If then the North part of the ſtone, whiche you holde in your hande, you turne to the South parte of that whiche floteth in the boxe, or otherwiſe the South part to the North, the floting ſtone ſhall turne toward your hand: and yf contrarywyſe, you turne the lyke part to his lyke, that is to ſay, the South part to the South &amp;c. the flotyng ſtone ſhal flye from you.<note place="margin">A queſtion of attraction of humours &amp;c. Scammonea, and chole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. A vire or a needle.</note> By this experience is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the reaſon of certayne Phiſitions, which diſpute on this maner. If <hi>Scammonea</hi> drawe vnto it choler by ſimilitude or lykeneſſe of nature, <hi>ergo</hi> muche more ſhoulde one <hi>Magnes</hi> draw another, rather then iron: for that which they aſſume falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we haue nowe taught to be true. The lyke iudgement is of a longe ſlender iron that is rubbed with this ſtone: for yf in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it be layde on a lyght peece of wood, or a ſtrawe, or ſuch lyke, ſo that it may freely flote vpon the water, the one ende of it ſhall turne to the North, and the other to the South. And yf holdyng the ſtone in your hand, you turne his North poynt to the South extremitie or end, or contrarywiſe, the ſtone ſhal then draw iron. But contrarily,<note place="margin">
                     <p>How the stone draweth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ron or ariueth it away.</p>
                     <p>Agent and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</p>
                  </note> if you turne the lyke part to the lyke (as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd)
<figure>
                     <figDesc>two lodestones with poles marked</figDesc>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>A. The North part.</item>
                           <item>D. The South part.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </figure> it ſhall flye from the iron, or dryue it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. The reaſon wherof ſeemeth to be, that the agent doth not onely endeuour to make the patient lyke vnto it ſelfe, but alſo in ſuch ſort to vnite it with himſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of them two be made one, as may appeare by this reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Take the ſtone <hi>Magnes</hi> A D. of the which A ſignifieth the North poynt, and D. the South.<note place="margin">The ſtone di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided in the mydde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</note> Diuide the ſtone in two parts AB. and C D. put A B. to the water as is ſayde, and by this meanes you ſhall ſee A. turne to the North, and B. to the South. For the
<pb facs="tcp:1369:9"/> breakyng or diuidyng of the ſtone, diminiſh not the vertue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo that it be <hi>Homogenie,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, in all partes alike. Take ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore A B. for the patient, and CD. for the agent. Then wheras the agent, in the beſt maner it may, woorketh to conſerue the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of nature, it is manifeſt that D. can not drawe C. the South: For although they coulde by that meanes be ioyned, yet ſhoulde there not ſo be made one of them two, the partes remaynyng in theyr vertue: for yf A. ſhoulde remayne North, then D. ſhoulde be South, whiche is certayne to haue the powre of the North.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depictions of lodestones with incompatible poles</figDesc>
                     <figure>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Impoſsible.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Impoſsible.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </figure>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>lodestones with proper poles</figDesc>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Naturall.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </figure>Neyther contrariwyſe ſhal C. draw A. for both are Northly, and ſo ſhould B be the North whiche fyrſte was South, and D. in lyke maner: for ſo ſhould the order of nature be inuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. It remaineth therfore that A ſhal naturally draw D. &amp; B. ſhal draw C. For ſo euery way ſhall remayne equall ſtrength of al.<note place="margin">From whence the stone hath his vertue.</note> Some ignorant men were of opinion that the vertue of the ſtone <hi>Magnes,</hi> commeth not of heauen, but rather of the nature of the place where it is engendred, ſaying that the mines thereof are founde in the North, and that therefore euer one part of the ſtone extendeth towarde North. But theſe are ignoraunt that this ſtone is alſo founde in other places. Wherof it ſhould folow that it ſhoulde then extende it ſelfe aſwell to other and diuers partes, as to the North. Which thing is falſe, as is wel knowen
<pb facs="tcp:1369:9"/> by common experience, for it euer moueth to the North in what ſo euer place it be. Neyther is it to be beleeued,<note place="margin">The North starre is not the Pole.</note> that the North ſtarre of the Mariners is the Pole: for as muche as that ſtarre is without the Meridian lyne, and but twyſe within one reuolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the fyrmament. But whereas the marueylous vertue of
<figure>
                     <figDesc>hollow globe</figDesc>
                  </figure> this ſtone dependeth of heauen,<note place="margin">Euery part of this ſtone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſome part of heau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> who would beleue that only two poyntes thereof ſhoulde ſo haue them ſelues, and not rather that euery parte of it ſhould not enclyne to ſome lyke part in heauen, as may thus be prooued. Let the ſtone be brought into a Sphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall
<pb facs="tcp:1369:10"/> or rounde fourme, as is ſayde, and the Poles being founde in maner before declared, let it be turned vppon two pynnes, or Turners inſtruments, and there be pullyſhed, vntyl it be on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry parte of equall heauyneſſe, which you may wel fynde by often proouyng: for that parte that falleth downe is heauieſt, whiche done, fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e it a Meridian circle with a Horizon, wherin faſten two other pynnes,<note place="margin">The greateſt miracle in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall thinges.</note> vpon the whiche it may eaſyly mooue, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the Poles moſt exactly to the Poles of the world, the which yf it come wel to paſſe, reioyce that then you haue found almoſt one of the greateſt miracles of natural thynges. For you ſhal by this meanes ſee the Aſcendent, the place of the Sunne, and the lyke. &amp;c. at euery moment. But yf it fal not out according to your deſyre, you ought not to impute that to the art, but to your owne ignoraunce and negligence. For yf you execute al thinges duely, accordyng to the art, you neede not to doubt the ſucceſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The compoſition of Inſtrumentes by the ſtone <hi>Magnes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owe by this ſtone inſtrumentes maye be framed, by the whiche may be founde the <hi>Azimuthes</hi> of the Sunne and Starres (that is to ſay, Vertical circles) it ſhal not be neceſſary to ſhewe, for as muche as the ſame is eaſily done by the Mariners Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, or by the boxe with the <hi>Magnes</hi> or Lodeſtone incloſed, and flotyng aboue the water with a pynne erected, and in the vppermoſte parte diuided into 360 partes, after the maner of Aſtronomie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1369:10"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of magnetic compass</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of continual motion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom the begynnyng of the worlde, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner all naturall Philoſophers and Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matitians, with great expences and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, haue attempted to fynde out a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall motion or moouyng: yet vnto this day haue fewe or none atteyned to the true ende of their deſyre. They haue attempted to doo this with diuers inſtrumentes &amp; wheeles, and with quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyluer, not knowyng the vertue of this ſtone. Neyther can conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual
<pb facs="tcp:1369:11"/> motion be founde by anye other meanes, then by the ſtone <hi>Magnes,</hi> in this maner. Make a holowe caſe of ſyluer, after the faſhion of a concaue glaſſe, outwardly laboured with curious art of grauyng, not onely for ornament, but alſo for lyghtneſſe, for the lyghter that it is, ſo much the more eaſlyer ſhal it be mooued, neyther muſt it be ſo pearced through, that ſuch as are ignorant of the hyd ſecrete, may eaſyly perceyue it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourme of the ſtone.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>lodestone with two poles</figDesc>
                     <p>The Pole</p>
                     <p>The Pole</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>It muſt haue on the inner ſyde certayne litle nayles &amp; denti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles or ſmal teeth of iron of one equal weyght, to be faſtened on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> border or margent, ſo that the one be no further diſtant from the other, then is the thyckneſſe of a beane or thicke peaſe. The ſayd wheeſe alſo muſt be in all partes of equal weyght, then faſten the Exiltree in the myddeſt; vpon the whiche the wheele may turne, the Exiltree remaynyng vtterly unmooueable. To the whiche Exiltree agayne ſhalbe ioyned a pynne of ſyluer, faſtened to the
<pb facs="tcp:1369:11"/> ſame, and placed betweene the two caſes in the hygheſt parte, whereon place the ſtone <hi>Magnes.</hi> Beyng thus prepared, let it be fyrſte brought to a rounde fourme, then (as is ſayd) let the Poles be founde: then the Poles vntouched, the two contrarye
<figure>
                     <figDesc>lodestone device</figDesc>
                  </figure> ſydes lying betwene the Poles, muſt be fyled and pullyſhed,<note place="margin">Denticles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> litle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and the ſtone brought in maner to the fourme of an egge, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what narower in thoſe two ſydes, leſt the lower parte thereof ſhoulde occupie the inferior place, that it may touche the walles of the caſe lyke a litle wheele. This done, place the ſtone vpon the pynne, as a ſtone is faſtened in a ryng, with ſuche art, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the North Pole may a litle enclyne toward the denticles, to the
<pb facs="tcp:1369:12"/> ende that the vertue thereof woorke not directly his impreſſion, but with a certayne inclination geue his influence vpon the den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of iron. Euery denticle therfore ſhall come to the North Pole, and when by force of the wheele it ſhall ſomewhat paſſe that Pole, it ſhall come to the South part, whiche ſhall dryue it backe agayne: whom then agayne the Pole Artike ſhall drawe as appeareth.<note place="margin">Calculus, a litle rounde ſtone or ſmall weyght lyke a pellet or plomm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> And that the wheele may the ſooner doo his office within the caſes, incloſe therein a litle <hi>Calculus</hi> (that is) a litle
<figure>
                     <figDesc>lodestone device</figDesc>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>A. The ſtone.</item>
                           <item>B. The ſiluer plane.</item>
                           <item>E. Calculus.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </figure> rounde ſtone or peſſet of copper or ſyluer, of ſuche quantitie, that it may commodiouſly be receyued within any of the denticles:
<pb facs="tcp:1369:12"/> then when the wheeles ſhalbe rayſed vp, the peſſet or rounde weyght ſhall fal on the contrary parte. And whereas the motion of the wheele downewarde to the loweſt part, is perpetuall, and the fall of the pellet, oppoſite or contrary, euer receyued within any two of the denticles, the motion ſhalbe perpetuall, becauſe the weyght of the wheele and pellet euer enclyneth to the centre of the earth, and loweſt place. Therfore when it ſhal permit the denticles to reſt about the ſtone, then ſhall it well ſerue to the purpoſe. The myddle places within the denti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles ought ſo artificially to be made holowe, that they may aptly receiue the fallyng pellet or plommet, as the fygure aboue declareth. And briefly to haue wrytten thus much of continual motion, may ſuffice.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:13"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Of moſt ſwift Motion by <hi>arte of Nauigation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E intende nowe to ſpeake of moſte ſwyft motion, which to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſorte of men ſeemeeth incredible, for that the ſame maye be doone by ſaylyng in a ſhyp or other veſſell, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt what ſo euer moſte outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous courſe of any fludde or ryuer, and agaynſt moſt furious wyndes what ſo euer they be, euen alſo in deepeſt wynter and greateſt ſourges of waters. Neyther is it marueyle yf this be incredible to the vnexpert. For the common people counteth that for a miracle, which the expert Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titians knowe to be naturall and eaſie:<note place="margin">A strang ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed.</note> for yf it ſhoulde be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to the ignoraunt people, that anye man myght in the myddeſt of the waters and fluddes, deſcende to the bottome of the ryuer of Rene, his apparel remaynyng drye, &amp; no part of his body we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te, &amp; alſo to bryng with hym burnyng fire from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the water, it ſhoulde ſeeme to them a laughing ſtocke, a mockerie,<note place="margin">The ryuers of Tagus &amp; Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nubius.</note> and impoſſible. Whiche neuertheleſſe in the yeere 1538. in Toleto a citie of Spayne, in the moſt ſwyft riuer Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus (in the whiche golde is founde) runnyng agaynſt the courſe of the Sunne none otherwyſe then <hi>Danubius,</hi> and three other in the world, makyng theyr courſe from the weſt to the Eaſt, I, with twelue thouſand other perſons, ſaw in the preſence of Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the Emperour the fyfth of that name. Of ſuch other maruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous naturall experimentes, I neede not here to ſpeake muche. Other there be that dare affirme,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rueylous ſwiftneſſe of a ſhyp.</note> that a certaine ſhip was in ſuch ſort dryuen with violent wyndes and furious ſeas with ſo ſwyfte a courſe, that the Pilote ſtandyng in the keele of the ſhyp, neare vnto the maſt, ſhootyng an arrowe out of a croſſe bowe, the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe fel downe before his feete, and came not ſo farre as to the forepart or forecaſtle of the ſhyp. I haue hearde alſo of credible
<pb facs="tcp:1369:13"/> men, that a certayne Pilote <hi>Cantabrian,</hi> lying at anker at Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe, on a certayne Sunday after mornyng prayer,<note place="margin">Swyfte ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> after m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nyng prayer.</note> departed with full ſayles and proſperous wyndes, vntyll he came to the coaſt of Saint Iames in Compoſtella. And immediately retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng with lyke proſperous wyndes, came agayne to Antwerpe in the ſame ſhyp the Sunday next folowyng. The whiche I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye not, but may be done, yet not without great daunger of ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, eſpecially in the returne, the winde beyng at the South. Alſo in the yeere .1551. I had experience of a moſt ſwyft mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For, from Drepan of Sicilia and Trinacria,<note place="margin">Another expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of ſwift ſayly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the porte of the galles of Maltha (nowe being in place of the Rhodes, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe called of Saint Iohn in Ieruſalem) a certayne ſhyp with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out euer ſtrykyng ſayle, in .37. houres arryued at Naples. And yet are theſe places diſtant in latitude almoſt fyue degrees, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde ſome part of longitude: whiche on the earth correſpondeth or amounteth to foure hundred and fyue myles. Theſe motions, are cauſed by violent fluddes and outragious wyndes. The lyke alſo may be doone agaynſt the furie of wyndes and violence of fluddes, when neede ſhalbe for expedite cariage of vitayles by ſea, and euen in places where it is harde to come to lande, and this with ſmall labour, as hereafter I wyll playnely declare by Demonſtration: but oftentymes,<note place="margin">The differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ng.</note> moſt expert Pilotes and ſea men, do marueyle that ſaylyng in ſhyppes of the ſelfe ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng, weyght, content, or capacitie, framed alſo of the ſeife ſame ſhypwryght, furniſhed with equall ſayles, and all other thynges apparteining, yet to be of ſuch diuers ſwiftneſſe, that the one can not kepe equal courſe with the other.<note place="margin">The prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aming of ſhyppes.</note> Which marueiling douht<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe proceedeth of ignorance and lacke of knowledge of the due proportion of the frame of al ſortes of ſhippes: that is to meane, the deapth, breadth, heyght, and length (named by the maiſters, latitude, longitude, altitude, and profunditie.) The which yf they be vnknowen to the maiſter Carpenter or Shypwryght, two ſhyppes can neuer be ſo directed by equall courſe, but that one ſhalbe ſwyfter then another, as I playnely obſerued in the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Arſenaria, or Thunes, or Agolette:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in which amongſt in maner innumerable ſhyppes, and eſpecially Galleys, and
<pb facs="tcp:1369:14"/> foyſtes, were ſcarſely two or one of the ſame quantitie, heauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, greatneſſe, and capacitie, dryuen all with one wynde and equall ſayles, that kept equall courſe one with another: And this doubtleſſe onely by reaſon of the different proportion of the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, makyng, or architecture.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ryght and due proportion of what ſo euer Shyppe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the framyng of any maner of ſhyppe, the proportion of length, breadth, heyght, and deapth, ought moſt cheefely to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly obſerued, leſt the ignorance and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence of theſe conſyderations, ſhoulde hynder the ſwyfte courſe, and cauſe daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſhypwracke. The due proportion therefore of ſhyppes is, that fyrſte the longitude or length of the ſhyppe or veſſell what ſo euer it be, more or leſſe, ought to be diuided into .300. equall partes, as appeareth in the figure folowyng.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of ship</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Of the whiche partes .30. muſt be aſſigned to the heyght or
<pb facs="tcp:1369:14"/> depth, for the tenth part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole requiſite longitude or length: and to the latitude or breadth ſhall correſponde the partes of the ſayde longitude .50. or the ſyxth part of the longitude. The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo or tymber of the Shyp muſt be lyght, leſt too muche heauyneſſe of the matter ſhoulde hynder the ſwyfte courſe. And this proportion of Shyppes or other ſaylyng veſſelles, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhape or frame, is moſt conuenient, and no leſſe neceſſary: As for Scafes, Shyppes of burden, Galleis, double, triple, or quadruple (that is to ſay) of two, three, or foure men to an Ore. Alſo for Foyſtes, Pinaces, Brigantines, Eſpions, and ſuche lyke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the framyng and Architecture of the aforeſayde Shyp.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> HAVE often tymes attempted by Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical reaſon, howe and in what maner a commodious faſhion of Shyppes, or other lyke veſſelles may be inuented with ſmal la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and litle coſt, which may in ſhort tyme ſtryue againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe of whatſoeuer ſtrong fluddes or ryuers, as Rhene, Danubie, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſella, Scalda, and almoſt infinite ſuche other, boylyng and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng, through the abundance of great ſhowres, molten ſnowes, and furious wyndes, and this eſpecially for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of tranſportyng victualles, and ſuche other neceſſaries: In conſyderation wherof, the proportion fyrſt obſerued, and the ſayde Shyp or veſſell almoſte finiſhed, then muſt be made three holes from the Kele, towarde the forecaſtle or foremoſte part of the Shyp, as appeareth in the fygure by the letters ABC. In which holes, in tyme of the courſe, certayne engines of ſtrange and marueylous inuentions may be faſtened. In the poupe or hynder parte of the Shyp, maye be prepared (after the maner of Germanie) a litle Stoue or whotte houſe, where the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers maye commodiouſly reſt. Nowe the Shyp beyng
<pb facs="tcp:1369:15"/> thus prepared, the bottome thereof muſt be dreſſed with tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, and not with tarre, that it may mooue the ſwyftlyer.</p>
               <p>Thus hauyng abſolued the frame and proportion of the ſayde Shyp, the reſt of Mechanicall or handicrafte woorke, we leaue to the Carpenters and Shypwryghtes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To what vſe ſuche kinde of Shyppes or veſſelles may be applyed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T chaunceth often tymes, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in winter, that certayne floods and riuers ouerflowen with to much abundance of waters, doo with their violence refuſe all nauigations that may be made agaynſt their courſe, to the great domage and hurt of the Inhabitantes of many Townes and Cities, to the whiche they ſhoulde carrie victualles, and other prouiſions, agaynſt the courſe of the ryuers: And therefore in fauour of the common wealth, I haue inuented theſe kynde of Shyppes, that I may hereby, as by my ſeale, confyrme the good wyll I beare to our poſteritie. Nowe therefore it may ſuffice to haue ſayde thus muche of this ſwyfte motion whiche I haue prooued with myne owne ſtrength, and haue ſufficiently declared the framyng and vſe thereof:<note place="margin">It is eaſier to adde to inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then to inuent.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto it ſhalbe eaſye for all men to adde more, accordyng to the excellencie of their wyttes and experience. For in all ſciences it is eaſyer to adde to inuentions, then to inuent. Conſyder nowe what commoditie this may bryng to the Brabantines, ſaylyng from Antwerpe to Bruxels in the newe ryuer: For that which they attempt dangerouſly with great vexation and ſhoggyng in waggons by foule and tedious iourney,<note place="margin">The newe ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer from Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe to Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xels.</note> often wette to the ſkyn for the ſpace of one whole day, maye by water be doone more conueniently, in the ſpace of foure or fyue houres, euen agaynſt the ryuer and wynde.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1369:15"/>
               <p>And leſte the reader ſhoulde ſeeme to refute our ſayinges, whyle he thynketh thoſe thynges whiche he eſteemeth for mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, to exceede the limittes of nature,<note place="margin">A no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>le ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment.</note> I wyll ſhewe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly by one Demonſtration, howe a man may deſcende into the bottome of anye water or ryuer, his body remaynyng drye, as here before I haue affirmed, that I ſawe in the famous Towne and kyngdome of Toleto, before the Emperour Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the fyfth, and infinite other.<note place="margin">The water in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> But here muſte fyrſte be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydered, that naturally the water or ſea (as other Elementes) intendeth to Sphericall forme, and with his globoſite or ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ouerpaſſeth moſte hygh mountaynes. But agayne here ſhall ryſe an other doubt to the vnexpert. That is: If the ſea be hygher then the lande,<note place="margin">Why t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> about ouerflowe the lande.</note> howe is it then that it dooth not drowne and couer the earth? Whereunto I aunſweare, that the dryeneſſe of the earth maye ſo long reſyſte the moyſteneſſe of the water, vntyll it receiue or imbibe to muche moyſteneſſe, whiche may thus be naturally prooued. Fyll a cuppe or other veſſell with water or wyne to the brymme,<note place="margin">An experime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> ſo that the fulneſſe thereof maye ſeeme to ſwell as though it woulde ouerflowe the brymme of the cuppe. Then may you yet put therein many pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of golde, without ſheddyng of one droppe of water. But yf the extremitie of the brymme be once wette, immediately the water ouerfloweth, becauſe the dryeneſſe of the veſſell dooth participate the moyſteneſſe of the water: whiche is yet better prooued in maner as foloweth. Take a certayne quantitie of water, and ſprynckle it by droppes vppon a drye (or duſtie, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: ſo ſhall the droppes partly ſhewe a Sphericall and ſwellyng forme remaynyng. But yf the table before be neuer ſo lyttle wette with water, the droppes ſprynckled thereon, ſhall flote abrode, and keepe no Spherical or rounde forme, by reaſon of the moyſtneſſe whiche the table had before receiued of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. It hath alſo oftentymes chaunced,<note place="margin">The dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wning of certayne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that certayne Townes and landes haue ben drowned by ouerflowyng of ryuers neare vnto them. Neuertheleſſe, howe muche ſo euer ſuche waters increaſe and ryſe, there is no daunger, vntyll great ſhowres fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng from heauen, doo thorowly wette the banckes, rampertes,
<pb facs="tcp:1369:16"/> or calſeys of ſuche riuers. For when they (as we haue ſayde) be thorowly imbibed with moyſteneſſe, they cauſe the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng and breache, whereof foloweth the ouerflowyng and drownyng of the region: and this may ſuffiſe for aduertiſement. Nowe therefore I come to the experience aforeſayde, ſhewed at Toleto by two Greekes: who takyng a chaulderon of great ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſitie,<note place="margin">This experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be proued with a great bell.</note> and the mouth turned downewarde, and ſo hangyng it in the ayre by ropes, they faſten certayne poſtes and boordes or ſhelues in the myddeſt of the chaldron where they place them ſelues with the fyre. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make it hang ſtedfaſtly and equally, they compaſſe the circumference, brymme, or border thereof with leaden plommetes on euery ſyde equally, and made of equal weyght, leaſt any part of the circumference of the mouth of the chaldron when it is equally and ſoftly let downe into the water, ſhoulde ſooner touche the water then the whole circumference. For ſo ſhoulde the water eaſyly ouercome the ayre incloſed in the chaldron, and reſolue it into moyſture. But yf by due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion the chaldron thus prepared, be fayre and ſoftely let downe into the water, the ayre incloſed in the chaldron (by reſiſtance of the water) ſhall violently make hym ſelfe place, not admittyng the water to enter. So the men there incloſed, ſhall ſo long remayne drye in the myddeſt of the water, vntyll ſucceſſe of tyme doo by reſpiration debilitate and conſume the incloſed ayre, turnyng it into groſſe humiditie ingroſſed by the coldneſſe and moyſtneſſe of the water: but yf in due tyme the chaldron be ſoftly and equally drawen out of the water, the men ſhal remaine drye,<note place="margin">An other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the foreſayd expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment.</note> and the fyre not extinct, whiche alſo may thus be prooued: Take a cuppe of glaſſe of a certayne quantitie: the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the mouth wherof, ſhalbe broder then the circumference of the bottome. In the mouth let be faſtened a little ſticke, tying thereto a threede: On the ſtycke, faſten a little candle of waxe, whoſe lyght may come onely to the myddeſt of the cuppe, leaſt to muche neareneſſe of the water myght ſuffocate the candle. Then proportionally (as in the former experiment) put the cup with the burnyng candle into a veſſel ful of water, &amp; in due tyme drawe it out ſoftly and equally, ſo that no part of the mouth of the
<pb facs="tcp:1369:16"/> circumference therof be drawen out before the whole, or ſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye: ſo ſhall the candle remayne alyue, as it was before. Then be naturall and Mathematicall Demonſtrations. Let not therefore the ignoraunt condemne our wrytynges, before they knowe what maye be doone by experience.<note place="margin">A ſecrete kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, is no more a miracle.</note> It is nowe then no more a miracle, when it is knowen to be naturall: And thus is it in all other Sciences and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentes, whiche the common people thynke to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. As the lyke in growyng of certayne fruites, trees,<note place="margin">Ignorance cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> and herbes, by art ſo helpyng nature, that they may ſpring and growe before their naturall tyme, euen in the harte of Wynter. It ſeemeth alſo a miracle to the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that in the tyme of moſte temperate ſeaſon, and great calmeneſſe on the ſea,<note place="margin">Whirlepooles deuouryng Shyppes.</note> Shyppes behelde faſte immoueable in the myddeſt of the ſea, and ſodaynely ſwalowed into the bowelles of the earth: whiche neuertheleſſe is doone natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in maner of an earthquake, and by lyke natural cauſe. The reaſon whereof, is,<note place="margin">The lyke of earthquakes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>me, and vndermin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng.</note> that the ayre as a moſte lyght Element, incloſed in the bowelles of the earth, ſtriuyng euer naturally to the circumference of the earth, as vnto his owne region. But the pores of the earth beyng ſtronglye ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and the ayre thereby agaynſt his nature forcibly inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſtryueth by violence to bruſt foorth, and ſo cleauyng the earth in the bottome of the ſea, and great abundance of water fallyng into the breache,<note place="margin">The ſpirite of De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gorgon.</note> euen from the hygheſt parte of the ſea in that place, with ſwalowyng attraction of the fal, draweth downe with it ſodainly the Ship or Shippes, whiche at that tyme approcheth neare vnto the place of that whyrelepoole. Furthermore, anye ignoraunt man woulde hardly beleeeue that the ſalt water of the ſea maye be made freſhe, and potable to be dronke, whiche neuertheleſſe maye be doone naturallye, as hath been often prooued dyuers wayes.<note place="margin">To make ſaid water freſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</note> Some doo this (as is wrytten in <hi>Gemma Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophica</hi>) puttyng the ſalte water in a veſſell playſtered or cruſted ouer with cleane Waxe, whiche diſtyllyng
<pb facs="tcp:1369:17"/> through the ſtrayte and narowe pores thereof, leaueth the ſalt,<note place="margin">There is a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way.</note> which for his groſneſſe can not paſſe therby. The ſame may be done better by a Canon or Pype, fylled with grauell or litle ſtones, and that the ſalt water powred there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may diuers times paſſe through that Pype into an other veſſell.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>¶Of the Flowing, and Reflowing,</hi> (that is) increaſe and decreaſe <hi>of the Sea, with the cauſes therof,</hi> more exactly then hytherto hath been declared by any.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Heras heretofore mention hath ben made of the ſea and flowyng of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and diuers other motions, it may be conuenient to adde hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſayinges and wrytynges of the moſt expert and learned man, <hi>Fredericus Delphinus,</hi> Doctor of artes and phiſicke, and publique profeſſor of Mathematical ſciences in the famous vniuerſitie of Padua, touchyng the flowyng &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng, or increaſe and decreaſe, (otherwiſe alſo named acceſſe and receſſe, that is, commyng and goyng, or ebbyng and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) of the water of the ſea. Which flowyng and reflowing, ſome do alſo name, the falſe reſt or quietneſſe, or inordinate motion of the water of the ſea. And albeit diuers learned men haue intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of this matter, yet foraſmuche as ſome of theyr wrytynges are ſomewhat darke, and not eaſie of all men to be vnderſtoode, I haue thought it neceſſarye, partly out of theyr wrytinges, and partly by mine owne induſtrie, more clearly &amp; largely to entreat hereof, that the ſame may be the better vnderſtoode of all men.</p>
            <figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:1369:18"/>
               <head>A figure ſhewyng the beginning of the day increaſe at the Sunne riſing, and the beginning of the day decreaſe in the midday, and the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the night increaſe at the Sunne ſetting, and the beginning of the night decreaſe at midnight.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Secondaryly, is alſo to be knowen,<note place="margin">Eyght p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>yng.</note> that there be in heauen eyght poyntes for the flowyng and reflowyng, or increaſe and decreaſe of the ſea: of the whiche, foure are ſtrong, and foure weake. Of the weake, two are weake for the flowyng, and two for the reflowyng. Weake for flowyng, are the poynt of the Eaſt, and poynt of the Weſt, whiche are the begynnyng of the two quarters of flowyng. Weake for reflowyng, are the poynt of the South or mydday, and the poynt of mydnyght, whiche are the begynnynges of the two quarters of reflowyng: and theſe foure poyntes are diſtant the one from the other, by a quarter of heauen. Of the ſtrong poyntes, two are ſtrong for flowyng, and two for reflowyng. Strong for the flowyng, are the middle poynt betweene the Eaſt and the South in the daye quarter of flowyng, beyng diſtant from the Eaſt .45. degrees, and from the South lykewyſe: And the middle poynt betweene the Weſt and mydnyght, in the nyght quarter of flowyng, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng diſtant from the Weſt 45. degrees, and from mydnyght lykewyſe. Poyntes ſtrong for the reflowyng, is the myddle poynt, betweene South and Weſt, in the day quarter of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng, beyng diſtant from the South .45. degrees, and from the Weſt lykewyſe: And the myddle poynt betweene midnight
<pb facs="tcp:1369:19"/> and the Eaſt,<note place="margin">A right Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon is when both the poles lye in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, &amp; that is to them only which dwell vnder the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall. Poyntes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall vertue in moouyng the water of the ſea.</note> in the quarter of the nyght reflowyng, beyng di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from mydnyght <hi>.45.</hi> degrees, and from the Eaſt lykewyſe. And as the weake poyntes are diſtant one from the other by a quarter of heauen, ſo are alſo the ſtrong poyntes diſtant the one from the other by a quarter of heauen, to them that haue a ryght Horizon.</p>
            <p>It is thyrdly to be knowen, that beſide the aforeſayde eyght poyntes, to ſuche as haue a ryght Horizon, there be many other poyntes equipollent or of equall vertue. And ſuche be all the poyntes of heauen equally diſtant from the foure principal poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of heauen, whiche foure principall poyntes are, the poynt of the Eaſt, poynt of the Weſt, poynt of the South, and poynt of mydnyght, or from the foure ſtrong poyntes of heauen, whiche is all one, yet in quarters of contrarie operation. For all ſuche poyntes are equipollent or of equall vertue in moouyng the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſea: but in a ryght Horizon it is otherwyſe, as ſhal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare hereafter.</p>
            <p>It is fourthly to be knowen, that the Sunne and Moone euery moneth, are togeather in one ſigne, degree, and minute. And this ſo beyng,<note place="margin">The aspectes whiche the Moone ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth with the Sunne euery moneth.</note> is called the Coniunction of the Moone with the Sunne. From thence for the ſpace of eyght dayes, or there about, the Moone is departed from the Sunne by her proper motion by a fourth part of heauen: and this departyng is called the fyrſte quarter of the Moone with the Sunne. From thence in fourteene dayes, or thereabout, ſhe is departed from the ſunne by an other fourth parte of heauen, and ſo by the halfe of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and this diſtance is called the oppoſition of the Moone with the Sunne, or the ful Moone. From thence to <hi>.21.</hi> dayes or thereabout, ſhe is departed from her oppoſition with the ſunne or full Moone by an other fourth part of the heauen, commyng towarde the Sunne: and this diſtance is called the ſeconde qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ature of the Moone with the Sunne, and then the Moone is diſtant from the Sunne by a fourth parte of heauen, as it was diſtant in the fyrſte quarter, and ſo commeth neare to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction with the Sunne. From thence at thyrtie dayes, or thereabout, the Moone is agayne with the Sunne in coniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as it was fyrſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:19"/>
            <p>Fyftly and laſtly, is to be knowen that the Sunne &amp; Moone, both togeather euery naturall day (whiche is the tyme of <hi>.24.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 paragraph">
                     <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> houres, to the mouyng of the fyrſt moueable) are the cauſes of flowyng and reflowyng, or increaſe and decreaſe of the water of the ſea twyſe. Theſe declarations premiſed, and wel kept in memorie, let vs declare howe the Sunne and Moone both togeather euery naturall day; to the moouyng of the fyrſte moueable, are the cauſes of the flowyng and reflowyng of the ſea. For yf theſe declarations be well helde in memorie, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the quarters of heauen in whiche is the flowyng, and the quarters of heauen in whiche is the reflowyng, and whiche are the ſtrong poyntes for the flowyng, and ſtrong poyntes for the reflowyng, and whiche be the weake poyntes for the flowyng, and the we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke poyntes for the reflowyng: theſe (I ſay) beyng kept in memorie, al the narration of the mouyng, and falſe quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſea, ſhalbe cleare and manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt of all (as touchyng the flowyng and reflowyng of the ſea to the mouing of the firſt moueable) it is to be knowen,<note place="margin">The Sunne &amp; Moone beyng in con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ction, what effect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s they ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> the ſea.</note> that when the Sunne and Moone are ioyned togeather, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction is called <hi>Nouiluniun</hi> (that is) the new Moone, when they be moued to the moouyng of the fyrſte moueable (called <hi>Primum mobile</hi>) from the Eaſt to the South, becauſe the vertues both of the Sunne and Moone be vnite togeather, and both theſe Luminaries are moued continually to the moouyng of the firſt moueable by the quarter of the day flowyng, whiche is from the Eaſt to the Weſt, the day flowyng or increaſe of the ſea is continuall. And whyle they are moued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the South to the Weſt, becauſe they are moued continuall by the day quarter of the reflowyng, the reflowyng ſtyll continueth. And whyle they are moued from the Weſt to mydnyght, becauſe they are then moued by the quarter of the nyght flowyng, the nyght flowyng is agayne continuall.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 paragraph">
                     <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And whyle they are moued from mydnyght to the Eaſt, becauſe they are then mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the nyght quarter of reflowyng, the nyght reflowyng is agayne continuall. And thus twyſe in the naturall day is the flowyng or increaſe, and twyſe the reflowyng or decreaſe of the water of the ſea.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:20"/>
            <p>It is agayne ſecondarylye to be knowen, that when the Moone after her coniunction with the Sunne, by her proper motion is departed from the Sunne towarde the Eaſt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the order of the ſignes, goeyng towarde her fyrſte qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drature with the Sunne (whiche the Venetian Pilottes call, <hi>il Quartirune</hi>) euer before the Moone by her proper motion, come to that firſt quarter, whiche is the diſtaunce of the Moone from the Sunne towarde the Eaſt,<note place="margin">A quarter of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is three ſignes.</note> accordyng to the order of the ſignes, by a quarter or fourth part of heauen, when the Sunne is ſo muche aboue the Horizon of the Eaſt parte in quarter of the day flowyng, howe muche the Moone is vnder the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon of the ſame parte of the Eaſt in the quarter of the nyght re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng, becauſe then the Sunne is ſo muche diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng aboue the Horizon, as the Moone is diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng vnder the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon,<note place="margin">A tyme wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is neyther ebbyng nor flowyng.</note> they are equipollent and of equall vertue, therefore then is neyther flowyng nor reflowyng of the water of the ſea, but the water ſeemeth to ſtande: And then the Venetians ſaye, <hi>L'aqua è ſtanca.</hi> But when the Sunne by the motion of the firſt moueable, commeth neare to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon in the day quarter of the flowyng, the Moone by the ſame motion of the firſte moueable, depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſo muche from the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng towarde the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng: And then becauſe the Sunne is nearer to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon in the day quarter of flowyng, then is the Moone in the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Horizon in the nyght quarter of the reflowyng, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng is weakened, and the flowyng is fortifyed: and then the water of the ſea begynneth to flowe. And howe muche more the Sunne approcheth to the ſtrong poynt of the flowing, which is aboue the Horizon in the day quarter of the flowyng, ſo much more the Moone is departed from the ſtrong poynt of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon in the nyght quarter of the reflowyng, approchyng to the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, and therefore the flowyng continueth. But when the
<pb facs="tcp:1369:20"/> Sunne by motion of the firſt moueable, commeth to the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon in the day quarter of the flowyng, then the Moone is departed from the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, and is made neare to the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, and therefore the flowyng yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth: But when the Moone ſhall come to the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, ſhee then to the mouyng of the firſt moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, is moued by the day quarter of flowyng, approchyng to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon: And the Sunne, becauſe it is diſtant from the Moone leſſe then a quarter, ſhall lykewyſe be moued by the ſame day quarter of flowyng, approchyng to the weake poynt of the South re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng: And therefore becauſe both are mooued by the day quarter of the flowyng, the flowyng ſhall continue. And when the Sunne by the moouing of the fyrſt mooueable, commeth to the weake poynt of the South reflowyng, becauſe then the Moone is nearer to the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, then the Sunne to the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon in the day quarter of the reflowyng, the flowyng ſhall continue. And when the Moone ſhall come to the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng in the daye quarter of flowyng, the Sunne ſhall not yet be in the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng in the day quarter of the reflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe that the Sunne is diſtant from the Moone leſſe then a quarter, but wyll come to it: and then the Moone ſhall depart from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, and ſhalbe leſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from it then the ſunne from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng: and therefore the flowyng ſhall yet continue, vntyll the ſunne be ſo muche beyonde the South toward the Weſt in the day quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of reflowyng, howe much the moone on this ſyde the South towarde the Eaſt in the day quarter of the flowyng: And then the ſunne ſhalbe ſo muche diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng whiche is aboue the Horizon, beyonde the South in the day quarter of the reflowyng, howe muche the moone from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon,
<pb facs="tcp:1369:21"/> before the South in the day quarter of flowyng: And inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, the Sunne and the moone ſhalbe equipollent or of equall ſtrength, &amp; therfore ſhalbe no flowing nor reſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wing, as we haue ſayd before. And when he ſunne by the motion of the fyrſt moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ſhall come to the ſtrong point of reflowing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day quarter of reflowyng, the moone by the ſame motion of the fyrſt mouea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſhalbe departed ſo muche from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng in the day quarter of flowyng, commyng towarde the weake poynt of the South reflowing: and then the moone ſhalbe more diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, then the ſunne from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng: And ſo the ſunne ſhalbe ſtronger then the moone, and therefore then ſhall begynne the reflowyng, and ſhall continue accordyng that the ſunne ſhall approch to the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, in the day quarter of reflowyng: and the moone ſhalbe departed from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng in the quarter of the day flowyng. And when the ſonne ſhal come to the ſtrong poynt of the reflowing, the moone ſhalbe departed from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, and therefore the reflowyng ſhall yet continue. And when the moone ſhall come to the weake poynt of the South reflowyng, the ſunne ſhalbe departed from the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, in the day quarter of the reflowyng, commyng toward the weake poynt of the Weſt flowyng: Yet ſhall the ſunne be leſſe diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, then the moone from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, and therefore the reflowyng ſhall yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue. And when the ſunne ſhall come to the weake poynt of the Weſt flowyng, the moone ſhalbe neare to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, which is aboue the Horizon in the day quarter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng, and ſhalbe leſſe diſtant from it, then the ſunne from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon in the nyght quarter of flowyng, becauſe ſhe is diſtant from the ſunne leſſe then a quarter or fourth part of heauen: therefore the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng ſhall yet continue, vntyll the ſunne ſhalbe ſo much vnder the Horizon on the Weſt part in the quarter of the nyght flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, howe muche the moone is aboue the Horizon on the ſame part of the Weſt in the day quarter of reflowyng. And becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:1369:21"/> then the Sunne ſhalbe ſo much diſtaunt from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon on the Weaſt parte, in the nyght quarter of flowyng, as the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, on that parte of the Weaſt in the day quarter of reflowyng: then the Sunne and the Moone ſhalbe equipollent (that is) of equal ſtrength and vertue, and ſo ſhal there be neyther flowyng nor reflowyng. But when the Sunne, by the moouyng of the fyrſt mooueable, ſhall come to the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon in the nyght quarter of the flowyng, the Moone by the ſame moouyng of the fyrſt mooueable, ſhalbe departed as much from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is aboue the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon in the day quarter of reflowyng: And then the Sunne ſhalbe leſſe diſtaunt from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, in the nyght quarter of the flowyng, then the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, in the day quarter of reflowyng, and therfore the Sunne ſhalbe ſtronger then the Moone: and then agayne ſhall begynne the flowyng, and ſhall continue (as is ſayde before) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll the Sunne be ſo muche beyonde mydnyght towarde the Eaſt, in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, howe much the Moone on this ſyde mydnyght, toward the Weaſt, in the nyght quarter of flowyng, and then the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche diſtaunt from the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, as the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng: and then incontinent the Sunne and the Moone ſhalbe of equal ſtrength, and there ſhalbe nother flowyng nor reflowyng. But when the Sunne, by the moouyng of the fyrſt mooueable, commeth to the ſtrong poynt of the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flowyng, in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, the Moone by the ſame moouyng of the fyrſt mooueable, goeth backe, &amp; is depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as muche from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> night quarter of the flowyng, comming to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weake poynt of midnight reflowyng: And then the Sunne ſhalbe leſſe diſtaunt from the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, in the nyght quarter of the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, then the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of flow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng in the nyght quarter of flowyng and then ſhal the flowyng be weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the reflowyng ſtrengthened and the water of the ſea ſhall then agayne begyn to reflowe, whiche reflowyng ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb facs="tcp:1369:22"/> (as is ſayde before) vntyll the Sunne be ſo muche aboue the Horizon on the Eaſt parte, howe muche the Moone vnder the Horizon on the ſame parte of the Eaſt: And then the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche diſtaunt from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of the flowyng, howe much the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of the reflowing, whiche is vnder the Horizon in the nyght quarter of the reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng: and then the Sunne and Moone agayne ſhalbe of equall ſtrength, and there ſhalbe nother flowyng nor reflowyng. Then daylye (that is to ſay, in euery naturall day) ſhall returne the lyke change to this aforeſaid, vntil the Moone by her proper motion, ſhall come to her fyrſte quadrature with the Sunne, which the Pilottes or Mariners Venetians, cal <hi>il Quartirone,</hi> as I haue ſayde before.<note place="margin">The Moone being in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile aſpect, or at the firſte with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſome what effectes it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in ebbyng and flowyng.</note> And when the Moone ſhall come to her fyrſte quadrature with the Sunne, then when the Sunne ſhalbe in the weake poynt of the Eaſt for the flowyng, the Moone ſhalbe in the weake poynt of mydnyght, for the reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng: and then the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche diſtaunt from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, which is aboue the Horizon, on the Eaſt parte, in the day quarter of the flowyng, howe muche the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, which is vnder the Horizon of the ſame part of the Eaſt, in the nyght quarter of the reflowyng: and ſo the Sunne and the Moone agayne ſhalbe of equall force and power,<note place="margin">A very litle ebbyng or flowyng.</note> and there ſhalbe nother flowyng nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng notable, but onely ſmal, encreaſyng and diminiſhyng. And when the Sunne by the motion of the fyrſt mooueable, ſhal come to the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, on the Eaſt part, in the day quarter of the flowing, the Moone by the ſame motion of the fyrſte mooueable, ſhall come lykewyſe ſo muche to the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon on the ſame parte of the Eaſt, in the night quarter of the reflowyng: and continually to the diurnall or day motion, the Sunne ſhalbe diſtaunt ſo muche from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the flowyng, howe muche the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon, in the nyght quarter of the reflowyng, and continentlye the Sunne and
<pb facs="tcp:1369:22"/> Moone ſhalbe agayne of equall power, vntyl the Sunne by the moouyng of the fyrſt mooueable, ſhal come to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon: And then lykewyſe the Moone ſhal come to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon, becauſe theſe poyntes are diſtaunt one from the other by a quarter of heauen, as the Sunne and Moone are diſtaunt from them ſelues by a quarter of he. And when the Sunne by the motion of the fyrſte mooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ſhall departe from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon in the day quarter of the flowyng, commyng towarde the weake poynt of the South, reflowyng, the Moone by the ſame motion of the fyrſte mooueable, ſhall lykewyſe departe as muche from the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon, commyng to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, and the Sunne ſhalbe contynually diſtaunt ſo muche from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, howe much the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon, vntyll the ſame come to the weake poynt of the South reflowyng: and then the Moone lykewyſe ſhall come to the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng. And the Sunne and the Moone in all this tyme ſhalbe of equall ſtrength, and incontinently ſhalbe nother flowyng nor reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng notable, and ſhalbe after the ſame manner whyle the Sunne to the motion of the fyrſte mooueable, ſhalbe moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the South to the Weaſt, becauſe then the Moone by the ſame motion of the fyrſte mooueable, ſhalbe moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the Eaſt to the South: And lykewyſe, whyle the Sunne ſhalbe mooued from the Weaſt, to mydnyght, becauſe then the Moone ſhalbe mooued from the South, to the Weaſt: And lykewyſe, whyle the Sunne ſhalbe moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from mydnyght to the Eaſt,<note place="margin">Eyght daies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> becauſe the Moone ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be mooued from the Weaſt to mydnyght. And ſo in all the tyme of one reuolution of heauen, whiche is one daye naturall of foure and twentie houres, the ſea ſhall neyther flowe nor reflowe ſenſiblye, but ſhall ſeeme to ſtande, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Sunne and the Moone in all the tyme of that
<pb facs="tcp:1369:23"/> reuolution of heauen, ſhalbe euer of equall power, without any notable difference. And this chaunceth about the eight day after the coniunction of the Moone with the Sunne. And this falſe quietneſſe of the water of the ſea, the Venetians cal <hi>Acquae de fele,</hi> and vſe this manner of ſaying, <hi>Da gliotto, à inoue, Lacqua non ſi moue.</hi> From the eyght day to the nienth, the water mooueth not.</p>
            <p>When the Moone ſhalbe departed from the Sunne, beyond the fyrſt quadrature, goyng towarde her oppoſition with the Sunne, then euer vntyll the Moone ſhall come vnto her oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition with the Sunne, when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche aboue the Horizon on the Eaſt part, in the day quarter of the flowyng, how much the Moone is vnder the Horizon on the ſame part of the Eaſt, in the nyght quarter of the reflowyng, the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche diſtaunt from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of flowyng, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partyng from it by the motion of the fyrſt mooueable, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng to the weake poynt of the reflowyng, howe muche the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, whiche is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Horizon, in the nyght quarter of the reflowyng, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng to it by the ſame motion of the fyrſte mooueable: And then the Sunne and Moone ſhalbe agayne of equal power, and there ſhalbe neyther flowyng nor reflowyng. And when the Sunne by motion of the fyrſt moouable, ſhal come to the weake poynt of the South reflowyng, the Moone by the ſame motion of the fyrſt mooueable, ſhall approche or come neare as muche to the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, in the nyght quarter of the reflowyng: and then the Moone ſhalbe nearer to the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon, in the nyght quarter of the reflowyng, then the Sunne to the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of flowyng, becauſe the Moone ſhalbe ſtronger then the Sunne: And according that the Sunne by the motion of the fyrſt mooueable, ſhal approch to the weake poynt of the South reflowyng, the Moone by the ſame motion of the fyrſt moouable, ſhal approch as much to the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon. And ſo the
<pb facs="tcp:1369:23"/> reflowyng ſhall continue vntyll the Sunne come to the weake poynt of the South reflowyng. And when the Sunne by the motion of the fyrſte mooueable, ſhall departe from the weake poynt of the South reflowyng, and ſhalbe mooued by the day quarter of the reflowyng, approchyng to the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, the Moone by the ſame motion of the fyrſte mooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ſhall departe as muche from the ſtrong poynt of the reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon, in the nyght quarter of the reflowyng, and ſhe ſhalbe alſo mooued by the quarter of reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, as the Sunne commyng to the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, becauſe the Sunne and the Moone are diſtaunt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them ſelues more then by a quarter of heauen: And ſo both ſhalbe mooued by the quarters of reflowyng, and therefore the reflowyng ſhall continue, vntyll the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche beyonde the South, towarde the Weaſt, in the day quarter of the reflowyng, howe muche the Moone on this ſyde the South, towarde the Eaſt, in the day quarter of the flowyng. And then the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche diſtaunt in the ſtrong poynt of reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, in the day quarter of reflowyng, departyng from it by the motion of the fyrſte mooueable, towarde the Weaſt, howe muche the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of the flowyng, commyng to it: And ſo the Sunne and the Moone ſhalbe of equall force, and then ſhalbe neyther flowyng nor reflowyng. And when the Sunne by the motion of the fyrſte mooueable, ſhalbe departed from the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, which is aboue the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, in the day quarter of the flowyng, commyng to the weake poynt of the Weaſt flowyng, the Moone by the ſame moouing of the fyrſt moouable, ſhall approch as much to the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of the flowyng, and then the Moone ſhalbe nearer to the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, in the day quarter of the flowyng, then the Sunne to the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, in the day quarter of the reflowyng: and ſo the Moone ſhalbe ſtronger then the Sunne, and then ſhal begynne the flowyng. And as the Sunne ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually be departed from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, in the day quarter of the reflowyng, ſo the Moone continually
<pb facs="tcp:1369:24"/> ſhal approche to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, in the day quarter of the flowyng, and ſo the flowyng ſhall continue. And when the Sunne ſhal come to the weake poynt of the Weaſt flowing, the Moone ſhall yet mooue by the day quarter of the flowyng, becauſe the Sunne and the Moone are diſtaunt one from the other more then by a quarter of heauen: and then the Moone ſhalbe nearer to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, in the quarter of the day flowing, then the Sunne to the ſtrong poynt of flowing, whiche is vnder the Horizon, in the nyght quarter of the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, and therefore the flowyng ſhall continue. And when the Moone ſhall come to the weake poynt of the South reflowyng, the Sunne ſhall paſſe the weake poynt of the Weaſt flowyng, approchyng to the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon, in the nyght quarter of the flowyng, and then the Sunne ſhalbe nearer the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, which is vnder the Horizon, in the night quarter of the flowyng, then the Moone to the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, which is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of the reflowyng, and ſo the Sunne ſhalbe ſtronger then the Moone, and therefore the flowyng ſhall continue.<note place="margin">A long tyme of flowyng.</note> And when the Sunne ſhall come to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon, in the nyght quarter of the flowyng, the Moone ſhall not yet be in the ſtrong poynt of the reflowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of the reflowyng, becauſe the Moone is diſtaunt from the Sunne more then by a quarter of heauen, and therefore the flowyng ſhall yet continue, vntyll the Sunne be ſo muche vnder the Horizon on the Weaſt parte, in the nyght quarter of the flowyng, howe muche the Moone aboue the Horizon on the ſame parte of the Weaſt, in the day quarter of the reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng and then the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche diſtaunt from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon in the nyght quarter of the flowyng, commyng to the weake poynt of midnight reflowyng, howe much the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of the reflowyng commyng to it: and therefore the Sunne and the Moone ſhalbe of equal ſtrength, and then ſhalbe neyther flowyng nor reflowyng. Afterwarde, when the Sunne
<pb facs="tcp:1369:24"/> by the motion of the fyrſte mooueable, ſhalbe diſtaunt from the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon on the Weaſt parte, in the nyght quarter of the flowyng, commyng towarde the weake poynt of mydnyght reflowyng, the Moone by the ſame motion of the fyrſte mooueable, ſhall approche as muche to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of the reflowyng commyng to it. And ſo the Moone ſhalbe nearer to the ſtrong poynt of reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, then the Sunne to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the flowyng ſhall begynne, and ſhall continue in maner (as is ſayde) vntyll the Sunne be ſo muche beyonde mydnyght, toward the Eaſt, in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, howe much the Moone before mydnyght towarde the Weaſt, in the nyght quarter of flowyng: and then the Sunne ſhalbe ſo much diſtaunt from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, goyng backwarde from it towarde the foreſayde weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, howe muche the Moone from the poynt of the ſtrong flowyng, in the nyght quarter of the flowyng commyng to it: and then the Sunne and the Moone ſhalbe of equall force, and there ſhalbe neyther flowyng nor reflowyng. And when the Sunne by the motion of the fyrſt mooueable, ſhalbe departed from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, vnder the Horizon, which is in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, commyng towarde the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, the Moone by the ſame motion of the fyrſt moouable, ſhal approch as much to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, which alſo is vnder the Horizon, in the nyght quarter of the flowyng commyng to it. And becauſe then the Moone is nearer to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is in the nyght quarter of flowyng, then the Sunne to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is in the nyght quarter of reflowyng: then ſhall the flowyng begynne and continue in manner aforeſayde, vntyll the Sunne be ſo muche aboue the Horizon on the Eaſt parte, in the day quarter of flowyng, howe muche the Moone vnder the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, on the ſame parte of the Eaſt, in the nyght quarter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng. And becauſe the Sunne ſhalbe ſo much diſtaunt from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon,
<pb facs="tcp:1369:25"/> in the day quarter of flowyng, commyng by the motion of the fyrſt mooueable, towarde the weake poynt of the South reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, howe muche the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon, in the nyght quarter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng, commyng by the ſame motion of the fyrſt mooueable towarde it, they ſhalbe of equall force, and ſo ſhalbe neyther flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng nor reflowyng. And in this maner, the flowyng and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng ſhall continue in euery naturall day, vntyll the Moone ſhall come to her oppoſition with the Sunne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Moone being in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition with the Sunne, what effectes they haue in moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſea.</note>And when the Moone ſhall come to her oppoſition with the Sunne, then when the Sunne ſhalbe in the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, the Moone ſhal lykewyſe be in the weake poynt of the Weaſt flowyng: and then ſhal the flowyng begyn, and ſhall continue as long as the Sunne ſhalbe mooued to the moouyng of the fyrſte mooueable, from the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, by the day quarter of the flowyng, to the weake poynt of the South reflowyng. And the Moone then in al this tyme, ſhalbe mooued lykewyſe to the moouyng of the fyrſte mooueable, from the weake poynt of the Weaſt flowyng, by the nyght quarter of flowyng, to the weake poynt of mydnyght re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng: and then the flowyng ſhall ceaſſe, and the reflowyng begynne, and continue as long as the Sunne at the moouyng of the fyrſte mooueable, ſhalbe mooued from the weake poynt of the South reflowyng, by the day quarter of reflowyng, vnto the weake poynt of the Weaſt flowyng, and the Moone in all that tyme ſhalbe mooued lykewyſe to the moouyng of the fyrſte mooueable, from the weake poynt of mydnyght reflowyng, by the nyght quarter of reflowyng, vnto the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng: and then the reflowyng ſhall ceaſſe, and the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng ſhall begynne agayne, and ſhall continue as long as the Sunne ſhalbe mooued to the motion of the fyrſte mooueable, from the weake poynt of the Weaſt flowyng, by the nyght quarter of the flowyng, vnto the weake poynt of mydnyght re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng. And then the Moone in al that time, by the ſame moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of the fyrſt mooueable, ſhall lykewyſe be mooued from the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, by the day quarter of the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, vnto the weake poynt of reflowyng: and then the flowyng
<pb facs="tcp:1369:25"/> ſhall ceaſſe, and the reflowyng begyn, and ſhall continue as long as the Sunne, by the mouyng of the firſt moueable, ſhalbe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the weake poynt of mydnyght reflowyng, by the night quarter of the reflowyng vnto the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng. And then the Moone in all this tyme by the ſame motion of the fyrſte moueable, ſhalbe moued lykewyſe from the weake poynt of the South reflowyng, by the day quarter of the reflowyng, vnto the weake poynt of the Weſt flowyng: and then the reflowyng ſhall ceaſſe.</p>
            <p>And when the Moone ſhall paſſe her oppoſition with the Sunne by her proper motion,<note place="margin">The Moone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> goyng to her ſeconde quadrature with the Sunne, then when the Moone ſhalbe ſo muche aboue the Horizon on the Eaſt part in the day quarter of flowyng, how muche the Sunne vnder the Horizon on the ſame part of the Eaſt in the nyght quarter of the reflowyng, becauſe then the Moone ſhalbe ſo much diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of flowing wh che is aboue the Horizon in the day quarter of flowyng, how muche the Sunne from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon on the ſame parte of the Eaſt in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, then the Sunne and the Moone ſhalbe of equall power, and therefore ſhalbe neyther flowyng nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng. And when the Moone by motion of the fyrſte mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueable, ſhalbe departed from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, which is aboue the Horizon in the day quarter of flowyng, commyng towarde the weake poynt of the South reflowyng, the Sunne by the ſame motion of the fyrſte moueable, ſhall approche as muche to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon of the nyght quarter of reflowyng, commyng to it: and then becauſe the Sunne ſhalbe leſſe diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon on the Eaſt parte in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, then the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon on the ſame parte of the Eaſt in the day quarter of flowyng, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng ſhall beginne and continue. And when the Moone by the motion of the firſte moueable, ſhall come to the weake poynt of the South reflowyng, the Sunne ſhall yet be vnder the Horizon in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, becauſe the Sunne
<pb facs="tcp:1369:26"/> and the Moone are diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them ſelues more then by a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of heauen, and then the Moone to the mouyng of the firſte moueable, ſhalbe moued by the day quarter of reflowyng, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Sunne in lyke maner by the nyght quarter of reflowyng, commyng to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng in the day quarter of reflowyng, and ſo the reflowyng ſhall continue. And when the Moone ſhall approche to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng in the day quarter of reflowyng, the Sunne ſhall approche to the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, in the nyght quarter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng, and ſhalbe further diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of flowyng, then the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of the reflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, whiche is lykewyſe aboue the Horizon in the day quarter of reflowyng: and ſo the reflowyng ſhall continue, vntyll the Moone be ſo muche beyonde the South towarde the Weſt in the day quarter of the reflowyng, as the Sunne before the South towarde the Eaſt in the day quarter of flowyng: and then the Moone ſhalbe ſo farre diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng in the day quarter of reflowyng, howe muche the Sunne from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng in the day quarter of flowyng: and ſo the Sunne and the Moone ſhalbe of equall force, and there ſhalbe neyther flowyng nor reflowyng. And when the Moone by the motion of the firſte moueable, ſhall depart from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, commyng towarde the weake poynt of the Weſt reflowyng, the Sunne by the ſame motion of the firſte moueable, ſhall approche as muche to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, in the day quarter of flowyng: And then becauſe the Sunne ſhalbe nearer to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is in the day quarter of flowyng, then the Moone in the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is in the day quarter of reflowyng, the flowyng ſhall begynne and continue accordyng that the Moone, to the mouyng of the fyrſte moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ſhalbe departed from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, in the day quarter of reflowyng, commyng towarde the weake poynt of the Weſt flowyng: and the Sunne ſhall approche to the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, in the day quarter of the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng commyng to it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:26"/>
            <p>And when the Moone to the mouyng of the fyrſte mouea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſhall come to the weake poynt of the Weſt flowyng, the Sunne yet by the ſame motion of the firſt moueable, ſhall moue by the day quarter of the flowyng, becauſe the Sunne and Moone are diſtant the one from the other more then by a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of heauen: &amp; the Sunne ſhalbe more neare to the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g poynt of the flowyng, in the day quarter of flowyng, then the Moone to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, in the day quarter of reflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, and therefore the flowyng ſhall continue. And when the Sunne ſhal come to the weake poynt of the South reflowyng, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone ſhalbe vnder the Horizon on the Weſt part in the nyght quarter of the flowyng, and ſhalbe nearer to the ſtrong poynt of the flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon in the nyght quarter of the flowyng, then the Sunne to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon in the day quarter of reflowyng: And therefore the flowyng ſhall yet continue, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll the Moone be ſo muche vnder the Horizon on the Weſt parte, in the nyght quarter of the flowyng, howe muche the Sunne aboue the Horizon on the ſame part of the Weſt in the day quarter of the reflowyng. And then the Moone ſhalbe ſo muche diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, vnder the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon in the nyght quarter of flowyng, commyng towarde the weake poynt of mydnyght reflowyng, howe muche the Sunne from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of reflowyng commyng to it: and ſo the Sunne and Moone ſhalbe of equall ſtrength, and then ſhalbe neyther flowyng nor reflowyng. And when the Moone by the motion of the fyrſte moueable, ſhall departe from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng vnder the Horizon, in the nyght qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ter of flowyng, commyng towarde the weake poynt of mydnyght reflowyng, the Sunne by the ſame motion of the firſte moueable, ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche as muche to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of reflowyng commyng to it: And then the Sunne ſhalbe nearer to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of reflowyng, then the Moone to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon, in the nyght quarter of flowyng
<pb facs="tcp:1369:27"/> And therefore then ſhall begynne the reflowyng, and ſhal conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue accordyng that the Moone ſhall departe from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon in the nyght quarter of flowyng, approchyng vnto the weake poynt of myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyght reflowyng, and the Sunne ſhall approche to the ſtrong poynt of reflowing, which is aboue the Horizon in the day quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of reflowyng. And when the Moone by the motion of the firſt moueable, ſhall come to the weake poynt of mydnyght re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng, the Sunne ſhal yet be aboue the Horizon on the Weſt part in the day quarter of reflowyng, commyng by the motion of the firſt moueable, to the weake poynt of the Weſt flowyng, becauſe the Sunne and the Moone are diſtant one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more then by a quarter: And then the Sunne ſhalbe more diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon on the Weſt part in the quarter of the nyght flowyng, then the Moone from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, which alſo is vnder the Horizon on the part of the Eaſt in the night quarter of reflowyng. And therefore the reflowyng ſhall continue vntyll the Moone be ſo muche beyonde mydnyght towarde the Eaſt, how much the Sunne before mydnyght towarde the Weſt: and then the Moone ſhalbe ſo farre diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, goyng from it by the motion of the firſte moueable, and commyng to the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, howe muche the Sunne from the poynt of flowyng in the nyght quarter of flowyng, commyng to it by the ſame motion of the firſte moueable: and ſo the Sunne and the Moone ſhalbe of equall force, and then ſhalbe neyther flowyng nor reflowyng. And when the Moone by the motion of the firſt moueable, ſhalbe departed from the ſtrong poynt of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon, on the Eaſt parte of the nyght quarter of reflowing toward the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, the Sunne by the ſame mouyng of the fyrſt moueable, ſhall approche as muche to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon on the Weſt part in the nyght quarter of flowyng commyng to it: And then becauſe the Moone ſhalbe more diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, then the Sunne from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, then ſhal begyn the flowyng,
<pb facs="tcp:1369:27"/> becauſe the Sunne ſhalbe ſtronger then the Moone. And howe muche more the Moone ſhalbe diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, ſo much more the Sunne ſhall approch to the ſtrong poynt of flowing, in the night quarter of flowyng, and ſo the flowyng ſhall continue: and when the Moone ſhall come to the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, the Sunne ſhall yet be in the nyght quarter of flowyng, becauſe the Sunne is diſtant from the Moone more then by a quarter of heauen, and the Sunne ſhalbe nearer to the ſtrong point of flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the night quarter of flowing, then the Moone to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, which is in the night quarter of reflowing: and ſo the flowing ſhal yet continue vntyl the Moone be ſo much aboue the Horizon on the Eaſt parte, howe muche the Sunne vnder the Horizon on the ſame parte of the Eaſt: And then the Moone ſhal ſo much be diſtant from the ſtrong point of flowing, whiche is aboue the Horizon in the day quarter of flowyng, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partyng from it by the motion of the firſt moueable towarde the weake poynt of the South reflowyng, howe muche the Sunne from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, which is vnder the Horizon in the night quarter of reflowyng, commyng to it by the ſame motion of the firſt moueable. And then the Sunne &amp; the Moone ſhalbe of equall force, and there ſhalbe neyther flowyng nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng, and the firſt diſpoſition ſhall returne agayne, and ſuche flowyng and reflowyng, ſhall continue euery natural day in this maner, vntyll the Moone ſhall come to her quadrature with the Sunne.</p>
            <p>And when the Moone ſhalbe in the ſeconde quadrature,<note place="margin">The Moone beyng in the laſt quarter, cauſeth the ſame effectes as in the first.</note> then the water of the ſea, ſhall neyther flowe nor reflowe, but ſhall ſeeme to be at reſt as it was in the firſt quadrature, in the which, in the whole reuolution of heauen, the Sunne and the Moone were euer of equall ſtrength for the cauſes there declared: for the ſame are the cauſes of the ſeconde quadrature, which are alſo of the fyrſt, and is about .21. dayes. And this quietnes or ſtay of the water of the ſea (as is ſayde before) the Venetians call <hi>Acqua de fele,</hi> and vſe this ſaying: <hi>Da vent' uno à venti due, l'ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua non va ne ſu, ne giu</hi> From the .21. to .22. the water goeth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vp nor downe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:28"/>
            <p>And when the Moone by her proper motion ſhall paſſe this ſeconde quadrature, proceedyng to her coniunction with the Sunne, then the Moone ſhalbe diſtant from the Sunne, leſſe then the fourth parte of heauen. And then when ſhe ſhalbe ſo muche aboue the Horizon on the Eaſt parte, in the day quarter of flowyng, as the Sunne vnder the Horizon on the ſame parte of the Eaſt, in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, then the Moone ſhalbe ſo muche diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, which is aboue the Horizon, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day quarter of flowyng, commyng to it by the motion of the fyrſte moueable, howe muche the Sunne from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon in the nyght quarter of reflowing, going from it by the ſame motion of the fyrſte moueable towarde the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng: and then the Sunne and the Moone ſhalbe of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall power, and there ſhalbe neyther flowyng nor reflowyng. And when the Moone by the motion of the fyrſt moueable, ſhall come to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon in the day quarter of flowyng, the Sunne by the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the firſt moueable, ſhall depart as muche from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, toward the weake poynt of the Eaſt flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng. And then becauſe the Moone ſhalbe leſſe diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of flowyng, then the Sunne from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, the Moone ſhalbe ſtronger then the Sunne, and therefore then ſhall begynne the flowyng: and howe much more the Moone ſhall approche to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, ſo muche more the Sunne ſhalbe diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, approching to the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowing, and therefore the flowyng ſhall continue. And when the Sunne by the mouyng of the fyrſte moueable, ſhall come to the weake poynt of the Eaſt flowyng, becauſe the Moone ſhall yet be in the day quarter of flowyng, for that ſhe is diſtant from the Sunne leſſe then a fourth parte of heauen, ſhe ſhalbe leſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, whiche is aboue the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, in the day quarter of flowyng, then the Sunne from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is vnder the Horizon, in the
<pb facs="tcp:1369:28"/> nyght quarter of reflowyng, therefore the flowyng ſhall yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue. And when the Moone ſhall come to the weake point of the South reflowyng, the Sunne ſhalbe aboue the Horizon, in the day quarter of flowyng, and ſhalbe nearer to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, then the Moone to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, whiche is after mydday (or the South) in the day quarter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng, becauſe the Sunne is diſtant from the Moone leſſe then the fourth parte of heauen, and therefore the flowyng ſhall continue vntyll the Moone be ſo muche beyonde the South towarde the Weſt, in the day quarter of reflowyng, howe muche the Sunne before the South towarde the Eaſt, in the day quarter of flowyng: And then the Moone ſhalbe ſo muche diſtant from the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, in the day quarter of reflowyng, commyng to it by the motion of the firſte mouea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, howe muche the Sunne from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, in the day quarter of flowyng, departyng from it by the ſame motion of the firſte moueable: and ſo the Sunne and the Moone ſhalbe of equall force, and there ſhalbe neyther flowyng nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng. And when the Moone by the motion of the firſte mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueable, ſhal approch to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, in the day quarter of reflowyng, the Sunne by the ſame motion of the firſt moueable, ſhall goe backe and depart as muche from the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, in the day quarter of flowyng: and then the Moone ſhalbe nearer to the ſtrong poynt of reflowyng, in the day quarter of reflowyng, then the Sunne to the ſtrong poynt of flowyng, in the day quarter of flowyng: and ſo the Moone ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſtronger then the Sunne, and therefore ſhall begynne the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowyng: and the flowyng and reflowyng, ſhall continue in the ſame maner as is ſayde.</p>
            <p>When the Moone departeth from her coniunction with the Sunne, and is not come to her firſt quadrature with the Sunne, and is betweene the coniunction and fyrſt quadrature, and when the Moone ſhall come to her coniunction with the Sunne, then agayne al the diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before declared, ſhal returne in al poynts in lyke maner as is ſayde.<note place="margin">A briefe col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of all the premiſſes.</note> Therefore this motion of the water of the ſea whereof we haue ſpoken, is a motion folowyng the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sunne &amp; Moone to the motion of the firſt moueable.
<pb facs="tcp:1369:29"/> For yf you ſhall wel conſyder that we haue ſayde of the flowyng and reflowyng (that is) increaſe and decreaſe, or acceſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the water of the ſea, you ſhall vnderſtande that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynges of ſuche flowyng and reflowyng, and lykewyſe the reſt and quietneſſe, chaunce diuerſly in the houres of the day and the nyght: For they come not euer in the ſame houres of the day, as is manifeſtly knowen to ſuche as obſerue ſuche flowyng and reflowyng, or falſe reſt or quietneſſe of the water of the ſea. And therefore by the aforeſayde dooth appeare that the water of the ſea hath motion of flowyng, once in the day, and once in the nyght: and lykewyſe of reflowyng once in the day, and once in the nyght.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ebhyng and flowyng begin not alwayes at one houre.</note>It is manifeſt alſo that the flowyng doth not begyn euer the ſame houre of the day or nyght, but at diuers houres: and lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe the reflowyng.</p>
            <p>Alſo the tyme of flowyng or reflowyng, proceedeth inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately when the Moone is in her quadratures with the Sunne, that is, in the firſt or ſeconde.</p>
            <p>There chaunceth ſometymes great increaſe of waters, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme leſſe, ſometymes meane, when the Moone ſhalbe in any other place from the ſunne beſide theſe foure: That is to meane, in the coniunction, or oppoſition, or her firſt quadrature, or ſecond with the Sunne.</p>
            <p>And as are ſometymes increaſes of waters, greater, leſſe, and meane, euen ſo are the decreaſes in lyke maner.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Great motio is of the water in the coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Sunne and Moone.</note>The greateſt concourſes and motions of waters, are when the Moone is in coniunction with the Sunne, &amp; alſo the greateſt flowynges and reflowynges. Lykewyſe in oppoſition of the Moone with the Sunne, and greater then in the tyme of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of the Moone with the ſunne. For the ſuperior bodyes, by their motion &amp; light, geue their influence into theſe inferior bodyes. And ſo much more as they haue of lyght, ſo much more &amp; ſtronglyer they worke:<note place="margin">Greateſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sunne and Moone.</note> and becauſe in oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Moone with the Sunne, the Moone is ful of light, &amp; her light is toward vs, therfore is it reaſonable y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> then ſhould be cauſed greater flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges and reflowyngs, then in her coniunction with the Sunne. Neuertheleſſe, becauſe that in her coniunction with the Sunne,
<pb facs="tcp:1369:29"/> the Sunne &amp; Moone are both vnite together, and their vertues, therfore alſo are great encreaſynges and decreaſyngs of waters, becauſe both their vertues are vnite, as I haue ſayde, but yet greater in the oppoſition then in the coniunction, for cauſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearſed.</p>
            <p>The Moone beyng in her quadratures with the Sunne,<note place="margin">Smal motions of the water without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate time alwayes in the quadratures of the Sunne and Moone.</note> the water of the ſea hath no determinate tyme of flowyng or reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, and then are the leſſe concourſes of waters, &amp; leaſt flowing and reflowyng. And ſuche motion of the ſea, the Venetians call <hi>De fele:</hi> and then the water of the ſea hath no determinate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng of flowyng or reflowyng, but is mooued inordinately in dyuers maner, ſometyme commyng, and ſometyme goyng. The cauſe of this diuerſitie is, becauſe the Sunne &amp; the Moone, where ſo euer they ſhalbe in moouyng to the water equally, or as it were equally, haue contrarietie in what ſo euer poynt they ſhalbe. For in what ſo euer poynt the Sunne ſhalbe, the Moone ſhalbe in the point of oppoſite vertue, contrary to the place of the Sunne, or neare.</p>
            <p>And when the Moone ſhalbe without the ſayde foure pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then the water of the ſea ſhal begynne to come or goe. And when the Sunne and Moone ſhalbe in equall poyntes of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the quarters of contrary operation, the concourſes of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhalbe ſo muche the greater,<note place="margin">Note.</note> in howe much the Moone ſhal be nearer to her coniunction with the Sunne, or to the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and ſo much the leſſe, in howe muche the Moone ſhalbe nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to the quadratures, lykewyſe alſo the flowynges and reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynges ſhalbe ſo muche the greater.<note place="margin">The Moone foloweth the Sunne in ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</note> For yf the Moone ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be betweene her coniunction with the Sunne and the fyrſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drature, then the Moone to the mouyng of the fyrſte moueable, dooth folowe the Sunne in his ryſyng: and then ſhalbe the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng of the day flowyng, of the day after the ryſyng of the Sunne, about three of the clocke, or before: that is to meane,<note place="margin">When flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng ſ al e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ares after Sunne ryſing.</note> when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche aboue the Horizon on the part of the Eaſt, in the day quarter of flowyng, howe muche the Moone vnder the Horizon on the ſame parte of the Eaſt, in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, becauſe then the Sunne &amp; Moone ſhalbe of equall force, becauſe they ſhalbe in the poyntes of equal
<pb facs="tcp:1369:30"/> vertue in the quarters of contrary operation, and the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the nyght flowyng ſhalbe in the nyght, after the fal of the Sunne (that is) when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche vnder the Horizon, on the ſame parte of the Weaſt, in the day quarter of flowyng, howe muche the Moone vnder the Horizon on the ſame parte of the Weaſt, in the day quarter of reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng:<note place="margin">Ebbyng after noone.</note> And the begynnyng of the day reflowyng ſhalbe in the day after noone, when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noone, in the day quarter of reflowyng, howe muche the Moone before noone, in the day quarter of flowyng: And the begynnyng of the reflowyng of the nyght, ſhalbe in the day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mydnyght (that is) when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche after the poynt of mydnyght, in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, howe muche the Moone before hym in the nyght quarter of flowyng. And yf the Moone be betweene the fyrſte quadrature and the oppoſition, the Moone yet in her ryſyng foloweth the Sunne, and then ſhalbe the begynnyng of the day flowyng, in the day after noone, about euenyng (that is) a litle before or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche aboue the Horizon on the parte of the Weaſt, in the day quarter of reflowyng, howe muche the Moone aboue the Horizon on the parte of the Eaſt, in the day quarter of flowyng, and the begynnyng of the nyght flowyng, ſhalbe in the day before day (that is) about mornyng, before or after (that is) when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche vnder the Horizon on the parte of the Eaſt, in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, howe muche the Moone vnder the Horizon on the parte of the Weaſt, in the nyght quarter of flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng: and the begynnyng of the day reflowyng, ſhalbe in the day before noone, when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche before the poynt of noone, howe much the Moone after the poynt of myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyght. And the begynnyng of the nyght reflowyng, ſhalbe in the nyght, before mydnyght, when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche before the poynt of mydnyght, in the quarter of the nyght flowyng, howe muche the Moone after the poynt of noone, or mydday, in the day quarter of reflowyng. And yf the Moone ſhalbe betweene the oppoſition of the Sunne, and her ſeconde quadrature with the Sunne, then the Moone in her
<pb facs="tcp:1369:30"/> ryſyng, goeth before the Sunne,<note place="margin">The Moone ryſing before the Sunne.</note> and then the begynnynges both of flowyng and reflowyng, be in lyke maner as they were when the Moone was betweene the coniunction and fyrſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drature. For the begynnyng of the day flowyng, ſhalbe in the day about three of the clocke, before or after (that is) when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche aboue the Horizon on the Eaſt parte, in the day quarter of flowyng, howe muche the Moone aboue the Horizon on the Weaſt parte, in the day quarter of reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng. And the begynnyng of the nyght flowyng ſhalbe in the nyght, when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche vnder the Horizon on the part of the Weaſt, in the nyght quarter of flowyng, howe muche the Moone vnder the Horizon on the parte of the Eaſt, in the nyght quarter of reflowyng: But the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng of the day reflowyng, ſhalbe in the day after noone, when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche after the poynt of the South, in the day quarter of reflowyng, as the Moone before the poynt of mydnyght, in the nyght quarter of flowyng. And the begynnyng of the nyght reflowyng, ſhalbe in the day, when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche after the poynt of mydnyght, in the nyght quarter of reflowyng, howe muche the Moone before the poynt of noone, in the day quarter of flowyng. And yf the Moone ſhalbe betweene the ſeconde quadrature, and her coniunction with the Sunne, then the Moone alſo in her ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng ſhall goe before the Sunne: and then ſhalbe the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynges of flowyng and reflowyng in the ſame houres,<note place="margin">Note.</note> as they be when the Moone is betweene the fyrſt quadrature and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: becauſe the begynning of the day flowyng, in the day after noone about euenyng, before or after, when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche aboue the Horizon on the part of the Weaſt, in the day quarter of reflowing, howe much the Moone vnder the Horizon on the ſame part of the Weaſt, in the nyght quarter of flowyng: and the beginning of the night flowing ſhalbe in the night, about mornyng, before or after, when the Sunne ſhalbe ſo muche vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Horizon on the parte of the Eaſt, in the nyght quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of reflowyng, howe muche the Moone aboue the Horizon on the ſame parte of the Eaſt, in the day quarter of flowyng.
<pb facs="tcp:1369:31"/> But the begynnyng of the day reflowyng, ſhalbe in the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noone, when the Moone ſhalbe ſo muche after the poynt of mydday, or the South, in the day quarter of reflowyng, howe muche the Sunne before it in the day quarter of flowyng, and the begynnyng of the nyght reflowyng ſhalbe in the nyght be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mydnyght (that is) when the Moone ſhalbe ſo muche after the poynt of mydnyght, in the nyght quarter of reflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, howe much the Sunne before the poynt of mydnyght, in the nyght quarter of flowyng. And hereby it appeareth, that as wel the flowyng as reflowyng of the water of the ſea, begyn not euer in the ſame houres of the day or nyght: for the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of flowyng is eyther in the begynnyng of the day, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng of the nyght, whiche chaunceth, the Moone beyng in coniunction or oppoſition to the Sunne: or is before day from the mornynges towarde the day, or from the day, vntyll foure of the clocke,<note place="margin">A general ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation for the beginnyng of ebbyng and flowyng.</note> or thereabout, or is before Euenyng, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde Euen tyde, and from thence to the Cocke crowyng, or thereabout: whiche chaunceth when the Moone is betweene her coniunction or oppoſition with the Sunne, or anye of the quadratures. The begynnyng of reflowyng is eyther at noone, or at mydnyght, as when the Moone is in coniunction or oppoſition with the Sunne, or is before noone, or after, or before mydnyght, or after, as when the Moone is betweene her coniunction or oppoſition with the Sunne, and anye of the quadratures. It is apparent alſo, that ſometymes the water of the ſea hath no determinate or certayne begynnyng, neyther order of flowyng or reflowyng, which chaunceth, the Moone beyng in her quadratures with the Sunne. It is manyfeſt alſo, that al flowyng of the water of the ſea, is cauſed by reſpect to the Horizon,<note place="margin">Note.</note> on the parte of the Eaſt or Weaſt. And euery reflowyng by reſpecte to the Meridian, or to the poynt of myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, or mydnyght.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In what Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe taketh place.</note>Here is alſo to be conſydered, that all that is ſayde, are moſte certaynely true in a ryght Horizon, but in an oblique or ſyde Horizon, they ſometymes fayle, as ſhalbe ſayde hereafter folowyng.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:31"/>
            <p>It chaunceth (as I haue ſayde) that the water of the ſea doth ſometime wander or decline from the order aboue preſcribed, yet commonly, and for the moſte parte keepeth that due order. Such maner of declynyng is after two ſortes: For there is eyther diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, or errour, in the houre of the begynnyng of the motion of the flowyng or reflowyng, or in the myddeſt of the motion: that is to meane, that they haue greater or leſſer courſes then at other tymes, or otherwyſe greater or leſſer increaſes and decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. The errour commyng in the houre of motion, may come of three cauſes: As, by reaſon of the ſituation of the region, or by reaſon of the bodyes ſuperceleſtiall, or by change of the ayre. By reaſon of ſituation of regions, chaunceth diuerſitie onely in the houre of the begynnyng of the flowyng,<note place="margin">The beginning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> becauſe the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng thereof hath reſpecte to the Horizon, or is by reſpecte to the Horizon: for in the begynnyng of reflowyng is no diuerſitie nor errour, becauſe the begynnyng of the reflowyng, is by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte to the Meridian circle. Agayne,<note place="margin">I he begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> by reaſon of the ſituation of the region, diuerſitie chaunceth thus, that is, that eyther the region is vnder the Equinoctial circle, or without it. And if it be vnder the circle, becauſe they haue a ryght Horizon, and the dayes be there euer equall with the nyghtes there, at all tymes of the yeere. That we haue ſayde of diuers houres of the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of flowyng, is certaynely true: But regions diſtaunt from the Equinoctiall, becauſe they haue a wyndyng or ſlope Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon in them, the begynnynges of flowyng are as in regions vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Equinoctiall, onely in two tymes of the yeere: That is to ſay, in the Spryng tyme, or Equinoctial Vernal, and in the tyme of Autumne, or Equinoctiall Autumna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, that is to ſay, About the myddeſt of the Moneth of Marche, and about the myddeſt of the Moneth of September: But in other tymes of the yeere, or from the Vernal Equinoctial, by the whole Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, vntil the equinoctial Autumnal, it is otherwiſe, becauſe the begynnyng of the day flowyng, yf the flowyng be before noone, that is, about the mornyng, it ſhalbe later then it ought to be: That is to ſay, more of the day then is in regions vnder the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall, and that becauſe, that in ſuche regions the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynneth ſooner, or the Sunne ryſeth ſooner, then in regions
<pb facs="tcp:1369:32"/> whiche are vnder the Equinoctiall: for the declynyng of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique or ſyde Horizon (although theſe regions be vnder one and the ſame Meridian.) But and yf the begynnyng of the day flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng be after noone, that is, about euenyng, then ſuche begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng ſhalbe ſooner then it is in regions vnder the Equinoctial, (that is to ſay) in fewer houres of the day: becauſe that then the Sunne falleth latelyer then in regions whiche be vnder the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial. But the begynnyng of the nyght flowyng, yf it be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mydnyght, it is ſooner in the ſayde places or regions (that is to ſay) in leſſe tyme of the nyght, or in leſſe tyme after the fal of the Sunne, then in regions vnder the Equinoctiall: becauſe that then the nyght begynneth to them afterwarde. And yf the begynnyng of the nyght flowyng be after mydnyght (that is) towarde the day, it ſhalbe later (that is) of more houres, or more neare the day, then is in regions vnder the Equinoctiall: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Sunne ryſeth ſooner to them,<note place="margin">Two flowyngs in one day, and none in the nyght.</note> then to thoſe that be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Equinoctiall. And this diuerſitie groweth ſo much, that ſometyme it chaunceth to ſee two flowings in one day, and none in the nyght: whiche chaunceth for the inequalitie of the dayes, with their nyghtes. For in howe much the artificiall day ſhalbe longer then his nyght, ſo muche ſuche diuerſitie and errour groweth more euidently. Therefore in the longeſt dayes of the yeere, ſuche diuerſitie ſhall appeare manyfeſtly. But from the Equinoctiall Autumnal, by al Wynter, vntyl the Equinoctial Vernall, it is contrary: becauſe the begynn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of the day flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, yf it be before noone, that is, about the mornyng, then ſhal it be ſooner then it ſhoulde be (that is to ſay) in fewer houres of the day, then it ſhoulde be in a ryght Horizon: for then the day begynneth latelyer, or the Sunne ryſeth latelyer to them that haue a wyndyng or crooked Horizon. And yf ſuch flowyng ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be after noone (that is) about euenyng, then the begynnyng of ſuche flowyng ſhalbe later (that is) more towarde the euenyng, or nearer to the fallyng of the Sunne, then in regions which are vnder the Horizon: For in ſayde or crooked Horizon, the nyght is ſooner, and the Sunne falleth ſooner then in a ryght Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon. Alſo, the begynnyng of the nyght flowyng, yf it ſhalbe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mydnyght, it ſhalbe later and more in the nyght, then in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions
<pb facs="tcp:1369:32"/> vnder the Equinoctial: becauſe then the nyght ſhal ſooner begynne in the crooked Horizon, then in the ryght, becauſe the Sunne fyrſte falleth in the crooked Horizon, then in the ryght. And yf the begynnyng of the nyght flowyng ſhalbe after myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyght, that is, towarde the day, then ſuche begynnyng of flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng in the crooked Horizon, ſhalbe ſooner (that is) in fewer houres of the nyght (that is) more before the day, or before the ryſyng of the Sunne, then ſhalbe in regions whiche be vnder the Equinoctiall: becauſe the Sunne ryſeth latelyer then in regions vnder the Equinoctiall. And ſuche diuerſitie groweth ſo muche, that ſometime ſhalbe two flowynges in the nyght, and none in the day: And this chaunceth for the inequalitie and encreaſe of the nyght aboue his day. For in howe muche the nyght ſhalbe longer then his day, ſo muche the more groweth ſuche diuerſitie: and therefore ſuche diuerſitie ſhall appeare greateſt in the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt nyght of the yeere. Wherefore, by the aforeſayde,<note place="margin">Note.</note> it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſt, that howe much the nearer we ſhalbe to the Equinoctial, ſo muche the leſſe ſhall appeare the diuerſitie in the houre of the begynnyng of flowyng of the water: And how much the Sunne ſhalbe nearer vnto the ſtandings or ſtayinges of the Sunne (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Solſtitium</hi>) or the longeſt daies, &amp; longeſt nightes, ſo much greater and more certaine ſhalbe the diuerſitie, and ſhal appeare more manyfeſtly. Furthermore, diuerſitie chaunceth by reaſon of the heauenly bodyes, and errour, not onely in the begynnings of flowyng, but alſo of reflowyng.</p>
            <p>For when anye of the great and luminous Starres (as are <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi>) ſhalbe about the Sunne or Moone,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>enes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And lyk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> they helpe them in moouyng the water of the ſea: and therefore by this meanes alſo, they haue their due order. Lykewyſe (as we haue ſayde) by reaſon of the change of the ayre, often tymes chaunceth diuerſitie and errour in the begynnynges of flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng and reflowyng: For the violent diſpoſition of wyndes, vehemently blowyng, as well neare, as farre of, remooueth the courſes of waters from their due order, ſometyme haſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the flowyng, and ſometyme the reflowyng, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme ſtaying or ſtackyng them lykewyſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:33"/>
            <p>There chaunceth alſo errour in the mydſt of motion of waters, for as wel courſes of waters, as alſo flowynges and reflowyngs, ſometyme keepe not the due motion: For (as is ſayd) the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of wyndes may either encreaſe or diminiſhe their courſes. Furthermore alſo,<note place="margin">Narowneſſe of places may cauſe diſorder.</note> the ſtrayteneſſe or narowneſſe of places, by reaſon of Ilandes or mountaynes, cauſe great concourſes and diuerſities in many places. For where the ſea is ſtrayter or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower, there is the ſtronger courſe, as about the Iland <hi>Fuboea, Nigropontis,</hi> and betweene <hi>Sicilia</hi> and <hi>Calabria</hi> is greatlye obſerued. Suche ſtraytes hynder the encreaſe of waters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe leſſe quantitie paſſeth thereby, and therefore there the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynges and reflowynges are leſſe. And herevpon it chaunceth, that in the Ocean ſea, are greateſt flowynges and reflowynges, becauſe there are no ſtraytes which may hynder or ſtay the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of waters, and by that meanes they haue their full and free courſe, and in more certayne order. But in our ſea, <hi>Mare Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diterraneum,</hi> it is otherwyſe. For what ſo euer water of the Ocean entreth therein, or commeth foorth, paſſeth from the Weaſt by one onely narowe ſtrayte: and therfore it can not in the flowyng be greatly fylled, neyther in the reflowyng be greatly emptied. And ſo conſequently, the motion of the water of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea procedeth not in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne order. And to haue ſaide thus much of the diuers motions of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea, may ſuffiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:33"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Demonſtration of Proportions <hi>of Motions Locall, printed rather</hi> for the learned Philoſopher, then the <hi>Mariner, yet the Mariner may learne many proper concluſions neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to be knowen.</hi> To the godly and not enuious reader, Iohn Taiſnier Hannonius, wiſheth health. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas a fewe yeeres paſt, at Rome, Ferraria, and in other Vniuerſities of Italie (when Paul the third poſſeſſed the Papal dignitie) I tooke in hande to reade publique lectures of ſciences Mathematike, I may teſtifie without ſcruple of arrogancie, that my lectures were honourably accompanyed with the preſence of more then three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred auditors, becauſe that artes Mathematike are there greatly eſteemed. And therefore after the lecture was finiſhed (as is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of auditors) oftentimes many reſorted vnto me, departing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſcholes, to demaund further of ſuch doubtes, wherof they had not ful vnderſtanding In the meane while, certaine which enuied my repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and aſſertions, ceaſſed not with iniuries, to hynder our procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, and ſometimes to make an ende of our disputations with quarrels and ſtrokes. It chaunced in the meane tyme that mention was made of the lecture of <hi>Ariſtotel.</hi> And whereas, from the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, one enuious perſon moued the question of the Proportions of Locall Motions, I refuſed to diſpute with hym, affirming that he euyll vnderstoode the intention of <hi>Ariſtotel,</hi> whom he ſo eſteemed as a heauenly God, that it ſeemed to hym ſacrilege, if any ſhoulde diſſent from his doctrine. But he, malitiouſly and furiouſly, affirmed that I dyd raſhly condemne <hi>Ariſtotel.</hi> I was therefore enforced by
<pb facs="tcp:1369:34"/> the requeſt of my reuerende Cardinal of <hi>Adulphis Florentine,</hi> openly to repeate the ſame, especially for that the reporte of theſe contentions, was nowe come to the Popes eares, whoſe requeſt alſo, I tooke for commaundement. And thereupon (whiche I had not doone before) I declared the errours of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> in the preſence of the reuerende Cardinal <hi>Creſcentius,</hi> and the Biſhop of Ponſet, men moſt expert in all kinde of learnyng, and in maner infinite other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditours, before whom (in maner as foloweth) I ſhewed the errours of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> by wordes and demonstrations. You therefore gentle and indifferent readers, accept this our Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration with fauourable myndes. I repute <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> for the chiefe of all Philoſophers. Yet foraſmuche as it is humane to erre, he alſo myght ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes fayle.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:34"/>
            <head>Demonſtration of the Proportions <hi>of Motions Locall, agaynſt</hi> Ariſtotle and all Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</head>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of weights</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>I wyll nowe make Demonſtration howe bodyes of the ſelfe ſame, or one kinde and figure, equall or vnequal one to the other, in the ſame middeſt or meane, by equall ſpace, be moued in one or ſelfe ſame time: the which is agaynſt <hi>Ariſtotel</hi> and all other philoſophers that haue not yet ſeene this propoſition. <hi>Ariſtotel</hi> firſt in the .4. of his phiſickes. Cap. <hi>De Vacuo,</hi> where he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to ſhewe, that yf <hi>Vacuum,</hi> or voyde, be graunted, mouyng or motion is taken away, &amp;c. he there ſayth thus, We ſee thoſe bodyes whiche haue more heauyneſſe or lyghtneſſe, ſo that they be of one figure, to be more ſwyftly moued by equal ſpace, and by ſuch proportion as they haue the one to the other. And therefore they are ſo moued, <hi>per Vacuum</hi> &amp;c. which is proued to be falſe. Furthermore what S. Thomas ſayth touchyng this,<note place="margin">Thomas de Aquino.</note> any man that wil, may reade: for no man euer better vnderſtood y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde
<pb facs="tcp:1369:35"/> of <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> But for the examples which <hi>Simplicius</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerroes</hi> geue to the vnderſtandyng of this (by two ſphericall bodyes of equal quantitie, but of diuers kindes, as one of gold, &amp; the other of ſyluer) we muſt not therfore ſay that they vnderſtood this propoſition as I wyll demonſtrate. For they ſhoulde haue ſayde ſomewhat of the equalitie of the quantitie of thoſe bodyes, foraſmuche as the motion of bodyes equall or vnequall,<note place="margin">Motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the bodies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and ſiluer.</note> is all one, ſo that they be all of one figure: as for example, yf there be three ſpherical bodyes, of the which two be of gold, and the thyrd of ſyluer, and they of golde be vnequall, and the other of ſyluer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to one of the golden bodyes: then in the ſame proportion of tyme, ſhalbe moued the golden body equall to that of ſyluer, with the ſyluer body, in the whiche proportion the ſyluer body with the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>den vnequall, as ſhalbe declared hereafter.</p>
            <p>Furthermore 6. <hi>Phiſicorum.</hi> Cap. 1. in the ende, and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner through al the .2. Chapter of the ſame booke, he confirmeth the ſame: but in the fourth he ſayth thus, Whereas euery thyng that moueth, moueth in ſome other, &amp; in ſome time, and that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueable is motion of the whole, the ſame or all one ſhalbe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions of the tyme and the mouyng, and of to be moued, and of that which is moued, and alſo of that in the whiche is mouyng. Afterward he geueth demonſtration after his maner: but cap. 7. he wylleth the ſame, where he intendeth, that in finite tyme, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng may paſſe into infinite greatneſſe. &amp;c. Furthermore <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> in his fyrſt booke, <hi>De Coelo,</hi> confirmeth the ſame, ſaying ſimply that the reaſon or conſyderation of tymes, is contrary to the reaſon of weyghtes: as yf halfe a weight be moued in this time, the double is moued in the halfe of this. &amp;c. And this cap. 6. Furthermore cap. 8. of the ſame booke he ſayth,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of fyre.</note> The fire in as muche as it is greater then the earth, ſo muche the ſooner and ſwyftlyer it commeth to his reſtyng place. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Alſo in his ſeconde booke, <hi>De Coelo.</hi> Cap. 8. he ſayth thus: As in other things, the greater body, is more ſwyftly moued by his proper courſe or motion, euen ſo alſo in the heauenly circles, &amp;c. Agayne Cap. 13. he affirmeth the ſame in two places,<note place="margin">Motion of heauen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſaying that the greater earth, is euer ſwyftlyer moued.</p>
            <p>Item, <hi>lib. De Coelo.</hi> cap. 2. he ſayth thus, If accordyng to
<pb facs="tcp:1369:36"/> the proportion whiche hath the ſpace C D. the body of B. ſhalb diuided, all B. in the ſame tyme ſhalbe moued by C E. in th whiche tyme parte of B. by C D. of neceſſitie: wherefore it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that B. be moued with ſwyfter motion then parte of B. Afterwarde he maketh lyke Demonſtration, ſaying thus, The ſwyftneſſe of the leſſe,<note place="margin">The greater body the quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker motion.</note> to the ſwyftneſſe of the greater, hath ſuche proportion as the greater bodye to the leſſe, &amp;c. Agayne in the thyrde, <hi>De Coelo.</hi> Cap. 5. in the ende he ſayth lykewyſe, that ſo muche the more euery thyng is moued, as it is the greater, as alſo the fire the greater it is, is ſo muche of ſwyfter motion, &amp;c. He confirmeth the ſame alſo,<note place="margin">The greater fire the ſwyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter motion.</note> Cap. 2. and 4. of the ſame booke, where yet ſpeakyng more clearely, he ſayth that the greater fire ryſeth vpwarde ſwyfter then a leſſe: and a greater peece of gold or leade, doth ſwyfter moue downewarde, and the lyke of other heauy bodyes: and more clearely can no man geather the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Perspectiue &amp; errour of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellio.</note>
               <hi>Vitel io,</hi> in his ſeconde booke of Perſpectiue in the ſeconde propoſition, hath fallen into the ſame errour. I pretermit his ignorance in that propoſition where he thynketh that there is no quantitie inſenſible: but let this paſſe with other errours, the whiche at any other tyme ſhalbe ſhewed in theyr place. He that wyll reade all other Philoſophers, ſhall ſee that they all accorde with the mynde and ſentence of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who alſo in diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places confirmeth the ſame: but to haue rehearſed theſe principall places, may ſuffiſe, and therefore we wyll nowe come to the Demonſtration.</p>
            <p>This propounded Demonſtration, I wyll ſhew apparently, that it may the better be vnderſtoode. And foraſmuche, as <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimedes</hi> in his woorke,<note place="margin">Archimedes.</note> 
               <hi>De inſidentibus aquae,</hi> hath ſpoken nothyng of the proportion of motion of Elementes, it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that he had not yet ſearched this propoſition: for there was the proper place of this matter. But it is not graunted to any one man to knowe all thynges: and therefore it was very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to many to imagine the ſuppoſition, whiche I openly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in Rome, whereas <hi>Archimedes</hi> maketh none other Demonſtration, but that naturall motion is not cauſed of any other then of the exceſſe or proceedyng of a bodye in an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:1369:36"/> aboue or vpon the ſayde Element, or contrarywyſe. &amp;c.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Demonſtration.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>And whereas by the 15. of the fyfth of Euclides, the proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe heauie bodyes, is the ſame which is betweene O. and G. by the .19. of the fyfth aforeſayd: the reſyſtaunce of the meane or myddle to O. ſhalbe quadruple to the reſyſtance to G. The ſame alſo doo I ſay of euery of the bodyes N L K H. It appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by common ſcience, that reſyſtance of the meane to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes N L K H. is equal to that whiche is to the body O. but is the ſame in the which G. by the fyrſt conception of Euclides.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>The lyke reaſon is alſo of violent motions, takyng the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of the moouyng ſtrengthes, and takyng away the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of the reſyſtaunce of the halfe or myddle.<note place="margin">Motions vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> Alſo, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as are two equall angles aboue the Horizon, or vnder, but in contrary order to the motion of nature, becauſe violent motion is ſwyfter in the begynnyng then in the ende: and the contrary
<pb facs="tcp:1369:38"/> chaunceth in the motion of nature: For with violent motion, the motion of nature is euer ſomewhat myxt, yf horizontally or angulerly it ſhalbe aboue or beneathe the Horizon: and nature woorketh ſo much, vntyl it bryng violent motion vnto ſome ende. But yf perpendiculerlye violence ſhalbe made aboue the Horizon, and towarde the place whiche that body natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally mooueth vnto, then nature can not ſtryue agaynſt or withſtande, but that violence doeth euer goe with it, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte of the ende from whence. Furthermore, by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde, it is manyfeſt that to be falſe whiche <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayth 7. <hi>Phyſic.</hi> in the laſt chapter, where he ſayth, Yf A. be that whiche mooueth B. and B. that whiche is mooued, and C. the longitude whereby, and D. the tyme in whiche the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, that is to ſay, in equall tyme and power equal. A. the halfe of B. ſhall mooue by the double of C. and by C. in the halfe of D. for ſo ſhalbe the ſimilitude of the reaſon. &amp;c. That it is falſe I wyll thus demonſtrate. Let vs fyrſt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine two bodyes as before, in any meane or myddle homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genie. &amp;c. As let be for example. M. and N. and that M. be double in quantitie to the body N and that the weyght of N. be al one with the weyght of M. And alſo that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy A V I. be equal to the body M. in quantitie, &amp; in lykeneſſe or kynde of the body N. Then by common ſcience, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy A V I. ſhalbe double in heauyneſſe to the body M. And grauntyng that the body M. be double in heauyneſſe aboue the halfe, then ſhall the body A V I. be quadruple in heauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe aboue the ſayde halfe. Wherefore the reſyſtance taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, let be left the tyme in the whiche the body A V I. to the tyme in the whiche M. is in proportion ſubtriple, or in the whiche the body A V I. in the ſame tyme ſhalbe mooued the body N. by the aforeſayd. Or yf in the ſame tyme the body N. ſhalbe mooued with the bodye M. yet the ſpace by the whiche N ſhalbe triple to that by whiche M. For the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is all one of violent motions. The ſame ſhall preciſely come to paſſe, yf in the ſteade of the exceſſe of weyght a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the halfe, we ſhal take the vertue or power moouyng &amp;c, as before.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1369:39"/>
               <figure/>
               <p>Wherefore it foloweth, that it may be done contrary to that whiche <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayth, and for the ſame ſentence of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſome haue thought that it is impoſſible that anye of the fygures of crooked lynes, ſhoulde be founde equal to any fygure of ryght lyne, or the contrary. The which to be poſſible, I wyll nowe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate. For example, let be geuen a <hi>trigon</hi> or triangle A B C. for that I ſay of the <hi>trigon,</hi> I meane alſo of all fygures of ryght lynes, for as muche as they be diuiſible into triangles, as appeareth by the 32 of the fyrſt. And yf of thoſe triangles we ſhal conſtitute a ſuperficiall lyne of equidiſtant ſydes, by 44. of the fyrſte, taken as often as neede ſhalbe, whiche duplicate by the helpe of 36. of the fyrſte, and afterwarde a Diameter in it, then the halfe of that <hi>ſuperficies,</hi> ſhall haue an equall trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle of the taken <hi>ſuperficies</hi> by the 41. of the fyrſte, or by the taken ryght lyne by the fyrſte conception, I wyll con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a ſuperficiall of two crooked lynes conteyned equall vnto it. I wyll diuide the fyrſte <hi>Baſis</hi> or grounde A C. by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall ſpaces into poyntes H. by 10 of the fyrſte, and I drawe B H. whiche alſo I drawe foorth vntyll H K. be double to B H. by 3. of the fyrſte twyſe aſſumpted. Then to the halfe
<pb facs="tcp:1369:40"/> of H K. that is I. I direct C I. and A I. I ioyne thereto alſo A K. and C K. by ryght lynes: then (by the fyrſt of the ſyxth) theſe triangles ſhalbe all equall to them ſelues. After this, I wyll conſtitute a ſuperficiall of equidiſtant ſydes, and of ryght angles vppon what ſo euer lyne, whiche <hi>ſuperficies</hi> ſhalbe equall to the <hi>Poligonic</hi> A B C K. by 44. of the fyrſte aſſumpted, as often as ſhalbe needefull, that <hi>ſuperficies</hi> is made G D. But in the whiche I drawe the Diameter F E. ſo that by 41. of the fyrſte <hi>trigon</hi> F G E. ſhalbe the halfe of the whole <hi>ſuperficies,</hi> and by common ſcience equal to the <hi>trigon</hi> B K C. and <hi>triplus</hi> to the <hi>trigon</hi> B H C. nowe I diuide F G. by equall in the poynt M. by 10. of the fyrſte, and I protracte or drawe foorth equidiſtantly G E. by 31. of the fyrſte. So doo I alſo of the lyne M L. diuiding it by equal in the poynt N. by the aforeſayde 10. of the fyrſte. Afterwarde by 44 of the fyrſte twyſe aſſumpted of equidiſtaunt ſydes, I make a <hi>ſuperficies</hi> of ryght angles vpon the lyne M N. equal to the quadrature of the lyne F M. which may conſyſt of M N. and N O. Furthermore, of M N. tranſuerſe or ouerthwarte, and N O. ryght, I conſtitute a parabol of a ryght angle, that it may be of leſſe labour: For this example may ſuffice by 52. of the fyrſt of <hi>Apolonius Pergeus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apollonius Pergeus.</note> the terminyng lyne of which paraboll, ſhall paſſe by the poyntes F N. and G. by the ſame, and by 33. of the ſame F E. ſhal touch the parabol at the poynt F. And afterwarde when the <hi>trigon</hi> F E G. ſhalbe <hi>triplus,</hi> to the <hi>trigon</hi> B H C. as we haue ſhewed before, but alſo the portion F N G. <hi>triplus</hi> by the 17. of <hi>Archimedes, De quadratura Parabolae.</hi> Wherefore the portion F N G. ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be equall to the <hi>trigon</hi> H B C. by the fyrſte conception in Euclide, added by <hi>Campanus.</hi> Furthermore, I drawe E G. vntyll by the thyrde of the fyrſte G R. equall G R. I drawe foorth alſo F R. and L M Q: Then by the fourth of the fyrſte, the triangle F G E. ſhalbe of equall ſydes, and alſo of equall angles to the triangle F G R. Furthermore, Q M is equidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant G R. by common ſcience, &amp; by R G. of the fyrſt, the angle F Q M. equal to the angle F R G. and the angle F R G. equal to the angle F M Q. and wheras the angle F R G. is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to
<pb facs="tcp:1369:41"/> eyther of them, then by the 4. of the ſyxt, the ſame, or al one, ſhalbe the proportion R G. to Q M. as is of G F. to M F. But as is G F. to M F. ſo is G F. to M L. Wherefore by N. of the fift, G F. ſo hath it ſelfe to M L. as G R. to Q M. But by the 16. of the ſame M L. to Q M. hath it ſelfe, as G F. to G R. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore M L. equall. M Q. whiche M Q. I diuide by equall in the poynt X by 10. of the fyrſt, &amp; wyl doo as before. Then by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aforeſayde of the ſame, the portion F X G. ſhalbe equall to the <hi>trigon</hi> A B H. and the whole Superficies F G. N X. ſhalbe equall to the whole <hi>trigon,</hi> A B C. whiche is propoſed.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>The contrary appeareth thus. Let be graunted a Superfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, conteyned of two paraboll lynes, as F N G. and F X G.
<pb facs="tcp:1369:41"/> propoſing (for example) to fynde a ſuperficiall of ryght lynts trianguler equal to the graunted ſuperficies. I drawe fyrſt F G. Then after by 44. of the ſecond of <hi>Apollonius Pergeus,</hi> I find the Diameter of the parabol F N G. whiche is M N. whiche I draw to N L. to be equall M N. Then I drawe F L. which ſhal touch the parabol F N G. in the poynt F. by 33. of the firſt of the ſame. Then from the poynt G. I draw a lyne G E. equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Diameter M N L. by 31. of the fyrſt of Euclide: whiche I drawe vntyll it ioyne togeather with F L. the whiche doubtleſſe ſhalbe done by the ſecond of the firſte of <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tellio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The poynt of the concourſe or ioyning togeather, is E. then I diuide F E. into three equal portions by the 11. of the ſyxth of Euclide, in the poyntes S. and T. which poyntes I ioyne with the poynt G. by the lynes F G. and G R. Nowe ſhall there be three angles all equall to them ſelues by 38. of Euclide. After this, I conſtitute a Trigon, B H C. equall to the Trigon, F S G. by this meanes I drawe foorth H C. to the equalitie G S. by the 4. of the firſt of Euclide. Then at the poynt H. I deſigne an angle B H C. equall to the angle F S G. by 23. of the firſt of Euclide: and by 3. of the firſt of the ſame, I drawe H B. vntyl it be equall F S. Afterwarde I ioyne B C. by a lyne. Then by 4. of the firſt, the tryangle B H C. ſhalbe equall to the triangle F S G. and ſhalbe equal to the portion F N G. by 17. <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes, De Quadratura parabolae,</hi> by the helpe of the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of Euclide. I do the like of the portion F G X to whom by an equall triangle O P R. Then I drawe P Q equally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant O R. and R V. equally diſtant O P. by 31. of the firſte of Euclide. Then by 41. of the ſame O P R. ſhalbe halfe of the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies</hi> O V. Now then I ſomwhat protract C H. then vpon B H. I conſtitute a ſuperficiall of equidiſtant ſides, hauyng an angle B H A. by 44. of the firſt of Euclide, twyſe aſſumpted: the Diameter of the which <hi>ſuperficies,</hi> be A P B. Then by 41. of the ſame with the firſt conception of the Trigon A B C. ſhalbe equal of the <hi>ſuperficies</hi> F G N X. graunted, which is the intent.</p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1369:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
